<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Propositions concerning the subject of baptism and consociation of churches collected and confirmed out of the word of God, by a synod of elders and messengers of the churches in Massachusets-Colony in New-England ; assembled at Boston, according to appointment of the honoured General Court, in the year 1662, at a General Court held at Boston in New-England the 8th of October, 1662.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R380</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12877529</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12877529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51037)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 721:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Propositions concerning the subject of baptism and consociation of churches collected and confirmed out of the word of God, by a synod of elders and messengers of the churches in Massachusets-Colony in New-England ; assembled at Boston, according to appointment of the honoured General Court, in the year 1662, at a General Court held at Boston in New-England the 8th of October, 1662.</title>
                  <author>Mitchel, Jonathan, 1624-1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. for Hezekiah Vsher at Boston in New-England,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Mass.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Chiefly the work of Jonathan Mitchel.</note>
                  <note>Caption title, p. 1, "The answer of the elders and other messengers of the churches, assembled at Boston in the year 1662, to the questions propounded to them by order of the honoured General Court."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Massachusetts --  Boston.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94891:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94891:1"/>
            <p>PROPOSITIONS CONCERNING THE SUBJECT of BAPTISM AND CONSOCIATION of CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES, Collected and Confirmed out of the WORD of GOD BY A SYNOD of ELDERS AND MESSENGERS of the CHURCHES in <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi>-Colony in <hi>New-England.</hi> Aſſembled at <hi>BOSTON,</hi> according to Appointment of the Honoured <hi>GENERAL CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT,</hi> In the Year 1662.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At a</hi> GENERAL COURT <hi>held at</hi> Boſton <hi>in</hi> New-England <hi>the</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>of</hi> October, 1662.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Court having Read over this Reſult of the Synod, judge meet to Commend the ſame unto the Conſideration of all the Churches and People of this Juriſdiction; And for that end doe Order the Printing thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Court. <hi>Edward Rawſon</hi> Secret'.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> for <hi>Hezekiah <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New-England.</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:94891:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94891:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>CHRISTIAN READER;</hi> And eſpecially to the Churches of <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi>-Colony in <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat one end deſigned by God's All-diſpoſing Providence, in leading ſo many of his poor people into this Wilderneſs, was to lead them unto a diſtinct diſcerning and practiſe of all the Wayes and Ordinances of his Houſe according to Scripture-pattern, may ſeem an Obſervation not to be despiſed. That we are fit or able for ſo great a ſervice, the ſenſe of our own feebleneſs forbids us to think. But that we have large and great opportunity for it, none will deny. For, beſides the uſeful Labours and Contemplations of many of the Lords Worthies in other places, and in former times, contributing to our Help, and ſhewing our Principles to be neither novell nor ſingular, the advantage of Experience and Practiſe, and the occaſion thereby given for daily ſearching into the Rule, is conſiderable. And He that hath made <hi>the path of the juſt as the ſhining light,</hi> is wont ſtill to give unto them further light, as the progreſs of their path requires further practiſe, making his <hi>Word a Lanthorn to their feet,</hi> to ſhew them their way from ſtep to ſtep, though haply ſometimes they may not ſee far before them. It is matter of humbling to us, that we have made no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter improvement of our opportunities this way; but ſome Fruits God hath given, and is to be praiſed for.</p>
            <p>In former years, and while ſundry of the Lords eminent Servants, now at reſt from their labours, were yet with us, <hi>A Platform of Church-Diſcipline,</hi> comprizing the brief ſumme thereof, eſpecially in reference to the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of Churches (which was our firſt work when we came into this Wilderneſs) was agreed upon by a <hi>Synod</hi> held at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and publiſhed to the world: From which (as to the ſubſtance thereof) we yet ſee no cauſe to recede. Some few particulars referring to the <hi>Continuation and Combination</hi> of Churches, needed yet a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite
<pb facs="tcp:94891:3"/>ſtating and reducing unto practiſe. For though the Principles thereof were included in what is already publiſhed, yet that there hath been a defect in practiſe (eſpecially ſince of late years there was more occaſion for it) is too too apparent: For the rectifying whereof, a more particular Explication of the Doctrine alſo about theſe things, is now neceſſary.</p>
            <p>In order hereunto, by the Care and Wiſdome of our Honoured <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court,</hi> calling upon all the <hi>Churches</hi> of this Colony, to ſend their <hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> this <hi>Synod</hi> was aſſembled, who after earneſt Supplications for Divine Aſſiſtance, having conſulted the holy Scriptures touching the Queſtions propoſed to them, have proceeded to the following Iſſue; hoping that if it might ſeem meet to the Father of Lights to guide the Churches unto a right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Practiſe of his Will in theſe things alſo, the beauty of Chriſt's wayes and Spiritual Kingdome among us would be ſeen in ſome more compleatneſs then formerly. For that which was the prayer of <hi>Epaphras</hi> for the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> ought to be both the prayer and labour of us all; <hi>viz. that we might ſtand perfect and compleat in all the will of God:</hi> And we truſt it is our ſincere deſire, that his Will, all his Will, and nothing elſe but his Will, might be done among us. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony</hi> we do wholly referre our ſelves, and if any thing in the following Concluſions be indeed found not to ſpeak according thereunto, let it be rejected.</p>
            <p>We are not ignorant that this our Labour will by divers be diverſly cenſured; ſome will account us too ſtrict in the Point of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and others too laxe and large: But let the Scriptures be Judge between us all, There are two things, the Honour whereof is in a ſpecial manner dear to God, and which He cannot endure to be wronged in; <hi>viz.</hi> His <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and His <hi>Grace.</hi> The Scripture is often putting us in minde how much the Lord loveth Holineſs, and that in his Houſe, and in the holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, and how he abhorreth the contrary, <hi>Mal 2.11. Pſal. 93.5. &amp; 2.6. Lev. 11.44, 45. Ezek. 22.26. &amp; 44.7, 8.</hi> And hence neither dare we admit thoſe unto the holy Table of the Lord, that are ſhort of Scripture-qualifications for it; <hi>viz.</hi> Ability to <hi>examine themſelves,</hi> and <hi>diſcern the Lords body;</hi> Nor yet receive or retain thoſe in Church-eſtate, and own them as a part of the Lords holy People, that are viſibly and notoriouſly unholy, wicked and prophane: ſuch we are bidden to <hi>put away from among us, 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>5.13.</hi> and therefore ought not to continue
<pb facs="tcp:94891:3"/>among us. Neither may we adminiſter Baptiſm to thoſe whoſe parents are not under any Church-power or Government any where. To baptize ſuch, would be to give the Title and Livery to thoſe that will not bear the yoke of Chriſts Diſciples, and to put the holy Name of God upon them, touching whom we can have no tolerable ſecurity that they will be edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the wayes of Holineſs, or in the knowledge and practiſe of Gods holy Will. <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which is the Seal of Memberſhip in the Church <hi>the Body of Chriſt,</hi> and an <hi>engaging Sign,</hi> importing us to be the devoted <hi>Subjects</hi> of Chriſt, and of all his holy Government, is not to be made a common thing, nor to be given to thoſe, between whom and the God-leſs licentious world there is no viſible difference: This would be a provocation and diſhonour to <hi>the Holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, we finde in Scripture, that the Lord is very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his <hi>Grace;</hi> that he delighteth to manifest and magnifie the Riches of it, and that he cannot endure any ſtraitning or eclipſing whereof, which is both deſhonourable unto God, and injurious unto men, <hi>Gal. 2.21. Eph. 2.7. &amp; 3.2, 6, 8. Rom 11.1, 5. Acts 15.10, 11. &amp; 10.15 &amp; 20.24, 26, 27.</hi> And in special he is large in the <hi>Grace of his Covenant</hi> which he maketh with his <hi>viſible Church</hi> and People, and tender of having the ſame ſtraitned. Hence when he takes any into Covenant, with himſelf, he will not only be <hi>their God,</hi> but <hi>the God of their ſeed after them in their generations,</hi> Geneſ. <hi>17.7, 9.</hi> And although the apoſtate wicked parent (that rejecteth God and his Wayes) do cut off both himſelf and his Children after him, <hi>Exod. 20.5. &amp; 34.7.</hi> Yet the Mercy and Grace of the Covenant is extended to the faithful and their ſeed unto <hi>a thouſand generations,</hi> if the ſucceſſive parents do but in the leaſt degree ſhew themſelves to be <hi>lovers of God, and keepers of his</hi> Covenant and <hi>Commandments,</hi> ſo as that the Lord will never reject them till they reject him, <hi>Exod 20.6. Deut. 7.9. Pſal. 105.8, 9. Rom. 11.16-22.</hi> Hence we dare not (with the Antipaedobaptiſt) exclude the <hi>Infant-children of the faithful</hi> from the <hi>Covenant,</hi> or from <hi>Memberſhip</hi> in the viſible Church, and conſequently not from <hi>Baptiſm</hi> the Seal thereof. Neither dare we exclude the ſame children from Memberſhip (or put them out of the Church) when they <hi>are grown up,</hi> while they ſo walk and act, as to keep their ſtanding in the Covenant, and doe not reject the ſame. God owns them ſtill, and they doe in ſome meaſure
<pb facs="tcp:94891:4"/>own him: God rejects them not, and therefore neither may we; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>their children</hi> alſo are not to be rejected. Should we reject or exclude any of theſe, we ſhould ſhorten and ſtraiten the grace of God's Covenant, more then God himſelf doth, and be injurious to the Souls of men, by putting them from under thoſe Diſpenſations of Grace, which are ſtated upon the viſible Church, whereby the children of God's viſible people are ſucceſſively in their Generations to be trained up for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, (whither the Elect number ſhall ſtill be brought in the way of ſuch means) and wherein he hath given unto Officers and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches a ſolemn charge to take care of, and train up ſuch, as a part of his flock, to that end; ſaying to them, as ſometimes to <hi>Peter, If you love me, feed my lambs.</hi> In obedience to which charge we hope it is, the we are willing and deſirous (though with the inference of no ſmall labour and burthen to our ſelves) to commend theſe Truths to the Churches of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that <hi>all the Flock,</hi> even the Lambs thereof, being duly ſtated under <hi>Paſtoral</hi> Power, we might after a faithfull diſcharge of our Duty to them, be able to give up our <hi>account</hi> another day <hi>with joy and not with grief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How hard it is to finde and keep the right middle way of Truth in theſe things, is known to all that are ought acquainted with the Controverſies there-about. As we have learned and believed, we have spoken; but not without remembrance that we are poor feeble frail men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire to be converſant herein with much humility and fear before God and men. We are not ignorant of variety of judgements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Subject; which notwithſtanding, with all due reverence to Diſſenters, after Religious ſearch of the Scriptures, we have here offered what ſeems to us to have the fulleſt Evidence of Light from thence; if more may be added, and may be found contained in the Word of God, this ſhall be no prejudice thereunto. Hence alſo we are farre from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that there ſhould be any rigorous impoſition of theſe things (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as to what is more narrow therein, and more controverſal among godly men.) If the Honoured Court ſee meet ſo farre to adde their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and concurrence, as to commend a ſerious conſideration hereof to the Churches, and to ſecure thoſe that can with clearneſs of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment practiſe accordingly, from diſturbance, that in this caſe may be ſufficient. To tolerate, or to deſire a Toleration of damnable Hereſies, or of Subverters of the Fundamenta's of Faith or Order, were an
<pb facs="tcp:94891:4"/>irreligious inconſiſtency with the love of true Religion: But to bear one with another in leſſer differences, about matters of a more difficult and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſal nature, and more remote from the Foundation, and wherein the godly-wiſe are not like-minded, is a Duty neceſſary to the peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of Religion, while we are in the ſtate of infirmity. In ſuch things let not him that practiſeth <hi>deſpiſe him</hi> that forbeareth, and let not him that forbeareth <hi>judge him</hi> that practiſeth, <hi>for God hath received him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as we do not thus ſpeak from doubting of the Truth here delivered (<hi>Paul knows</hi> where the Truth lyes, and <hi>is perſwaded of it,</hi> Rom. <hi>14.14.</hi> yet he can lovingly bear a Diſſenter, and in like manner ſhould we). So we do in the bowels of Chriſt Jeſus command the conſideration of theſe things unto our Brethren in the ſeveral Churches. What is here offered is farre from being any declining from former Principles, it is rather a purſuance thereof; for it is all included in, or deducible from what we unanimouſly profeſſed and owned in the fore-mentioned <hi>Platform of Diſcipline,</hi> many years ſince. There it is aſſerted, that <hi>Children are Church-members; That they have many priviledges which others (not Church-members) have not; and that they are under Diſcipline in the Church,</hi> chap. <hi>12.</hi> ſect. <hi>7.</hi> and that will infer the right of their children, they continuing to walk orderly. And the other matter of <hi>Conſociation,</hi> or exerciſe of <hi>Communion of Churches,</hi> is largely held forth <hi>Chap. 15. &amp; 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be an Objection lying in the mindes of ſome, and which many may deſire a fuller Anſwer unto; That theſe things, or ſome of them, are <hi>Innovations</hi> in our Church-wayes, and things which the Lord's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in <hi>New-England,</hi> who are now with God, did never teach not hold, and therefore why ſhould we now, after ſo many years, fall upon new Opinions and Practiſes? Is not this <hi>a declining</hi> from our firſt Purity, and a blameable Alteration? To this: Although it were a ſufficient Anſwer to ſay, That in matters of Religion, not ſo much what <hi>hath been</hi> held or practiſed, as what <hi>ſhould be,</hi> and what the Word of God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, ought to be our Enquiry and our Rule. The people in <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> time are commended for doing as <hi>they found written in the Law,</hi> though <hi>from the dayes of Joſhua the ſon of Nun, unto that day, the children of Iſrael had not done ſo,</hi> Nehem. <hi>8.14, 17.</hi> See the like <hi>2 Chron. 30.5, 26. 2 Kings 23.21, 22.</hi> they did not tye themſelves to former uſe and cuſtome, but to the Rule of Gods written Word, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:94891:5"/>ſhould we. It was <hi>Thyatira</hi>'s praiſe, that their good works were <hi>more at the laſt then at the firſt,</hi> Rev. <hi>2.19.</hi> The Lord's humble and faithfull Servants are not went to be forward to think themſelves <hi>perfect</hi> in their attainments, but deſirous rather to make <hi>a progreſs</hi> in the knowledge and practiſe of God's holy Will. If therefore the things here poopounded concerning the children of Church-members, and the Conſociation of Churches, be a part of the Will of God contained in the Scriptures, (as we hope the Diſcourſe enſuing will ſhew them to be) that doth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently beſpeak their entertainment, although they had not formerly been) held or heard of amongst us. Yet this muſt not be granted, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being the Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Points herein which may be moſt ſcrupled by ſome, are known to have been the judgement of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Elders of theſe Churches for many years, and of thoſe that have been of moſt eminent eſteem among us. As (beſides what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned from the <hi>Platform of Diſcipline</hi>) may appear by the following <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> from ſundry Eminent and Worthy <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> who are now with God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Touching the children of Church-members.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> hath this ſaying; <hi>The Covenant and Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>is that which we plead for, which the Apoſtle ſaith is come upon us Gentiles,</hi> Gal. <hi>3.14. which admitteth the faithful and their Infant-ſeed, not during their lives, in caſe their lives ſhould grow up to Apoſtacy or open Scandal, but during their infancy, and ſo long after as they ſhall continue in a viſible profeſſion of the Covenant and Faith, and Religion of their fathers: otherwiſe, if the children of the faithful grow up to Apoſtacy, or any open Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, (<hi>as</hi> Iſhmael <hi>and</hi> Eſau <hi>did</hi>) as they were then, ſo ſuch like now are to be caſt out of the fellowſhip of the Covenant, and of the Seals thereof.</hi> Grounds and Ends of Baptiſm of Children. <hi>p. 106.</hi> ſee alſo <hi>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.34.</hi> Again, <hi>The ſeed of the Iſraelites, though many of them were not ſincerely godly, yet whileſt they held forth the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick profeſſion of God's people,</hi> Deut. <hi>26.3-11. and continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wing of the Covenant, and ſubjection to the Ordinances, they were ſtill accounted an holy ſeed,</hi> Ezra <hi>9.2. and ſo their children were partakers of Circumciſion. Yea further, though themſelves were ſometimes kept from the Lords Supper (the Paſſeover) for ſome or other uncleanneſs, yet that debarred not their children from
<pb facs="tcp:94891:5"/>Circumciſion. Againſt this may it not ſeem vain to ſtand upon a difference between the Church of Iſrael and our Churches of the New-Teſtament — For the ſame Covenant which God made with the National Church of Iſrael and their ſeed, it is the very ſame for ſubſtance, and none other, which the Lord makes with any Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Church, and our ſeed.</hi> Quaery 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Accommodation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Presbyt. and Congregal. Churches. And the ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with thoſe Quaeries, was delivered by him in <hi>12.</hi> Propoſitions, as Mr. <hi>Tho: Allen</hi> witneſſeth in Epiſt. to the Reader before Treat. of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and thoſe Quaeries. Now in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of thoſe Propoſitions he hath theſe words: <hi>The children of Church-members with us though baptized in their infancy, yet when they come to age they are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to the Lords Supper, nor admitted to fellowſhip of Voting in Admiſſions, Elections, Cenſures, till they come to profeſs their Faith and Repentance, and to lay hold of the Covenant of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents before the Church; and yet they being not caſt out of the Church, nor from the Covenant thereof, their children as well as themſelves being within the Covenant, they may be partakers of the firſt Seal of the Covenant.</hi> Laſtly, ſpeaking to that Objection, <hi>That the Baptiſm of Infants overthrows and deſtroys the Body of Chriſt, the holy Temple of God; and that in time it will come to conſiſt of natural and carnal Members, and the power of Goverment reſt in the hands of the wicked.</hi> He Anſwers, <hi>That this puts a fear where no fear is, or a cauſleſs fear.</hi> And in proſecution of his Anſwer he hath theſe words; <hi>Let the Primitive Practiſe be reſtored to its purity,</hi> (viz. that due care be taken of baptized members of the Church for their fitting for the Lords Table) <hi>and then there will be no more fear of peſtering Churches with a carnal generation of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers baptized in their infancy, then of admitting a carnal company of hypocrites confeſſing their Faith and Repentance in the face of the Congregation. Either the Lord in the faithfulneſs of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant will ſanctifie the hearts of the baptized Infants to prepare them for his Table, or elſe he will diſcover their hypocriſie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs in the preſence of his Church before men and Angels, and ſo prevent the pollution of the Lords Table, and corruption of the Diſcipline of the Church by their partaking in them.</hi> Grounds and Ends of Baptiſm, &amp;c. <hi>p. 161, 163.</hi> See alſo Holineſs of Church-members,
<pb facs="tcp:94891:6"/>
               <hi>p. 41, 51, 56, 57, 63, 87.</hi> Bloody Tenent waſhed, <hi>p. 44, 78.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſaith, <hi>Suppoſe a whole Congregation ſhould conſiſt of ſuch who were children to Parents now deceaſed who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate their children were true members according to the Rules of the Goſpel, by the profeſſion of their fathers Covenant, though they ſhould not make any perſonal and vocal expreſſion of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement as the fathers did.</hi> Survey, part <hi>1. p. 48.</hi> Again, <hi>We maintain according to truth, that the believing parent covenants and confeſſeth for himſelf and his poſterity, and this covenanting then and now is the ſame for the kinde of it.</hi> Part <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>25.</hi> See <hi>p. 17, 18.</hi> &amp; <hi>part 1. p. 69, 76, 77.</hi> And in the Preface, fetting down ſundry things, wherein he conſents with Mr. <hi>R.</hi> he expreſſeth this for one, that <hi>Infants of viſible Churches born of wicked parents, being members of the Church, ought to be baptized. In theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſeveral other particulars, we fally accord with Mr.</hi> R. And Part <hi>3. p. 11. It is not then the Queſtion, whether wicked members while they are tolerated ſinfully in the Church they and their children may partake of the Priviledges? for this is beyond queſtion, nor do I know, nor yet ever heard it denied by any of ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Philips,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>a people made partakers of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and all the priviledges outwardly belonging thereto,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Themſelves and all that ever proceed from them, continue in the ſame ſtate, parents and children ſucceſſively, ſo long as the Lord continues the courſe of his Diſpenſation; nor can any alteration befall them, whereby this eſtate is diſſolved, but ſome apparent act of God break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them off from him.</hi> Reply, <hi>p. 126.</hi> Again, ſpeaking of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, <hi>1 Cor. 7.14.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I take it of foederal holineſs, whereby the children are with the believing parents taken by God to be his, and by him put under his covenant, and ſo they continue when men of years, though they never have any further grace wrought in them, nor have any other ſtate upon them, then what they had when they were born<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Ibid. <hi>p 131. Again, a company become or are a Church, either by converſion and initial conſtitution, or by continuance of the ſame conſtituted Churches ſucceſſively by propagation of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who all are born in the Church-ſtate, and under the covenant of God, and belong unto the Church, and are a Church ſucceſſively ſo long as God ſhall continue his begun diſpenſation, even as well &amp; as fully as the firſt.</hi> Ibid. <hi>p. 145.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94891:6"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Shepard in</hi> Defence of the Nine Poſitions, <hi>p 143.</hi> hath the expreſſion, <hi>Concerning the Infants of Church-members, they are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Cenſures whenſoever they offend the Church, as others are, though ſo long as they live innocently they need them not.</hi> And in the year <hi>1649.</hi> not three moneths before his Death, he wrots unto a friend a large Letter (yet extant under his own Hand) concerning the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip of Children, wherein he proveth by ſundry Arguments <hi>that they are Members,</hi> and anſwereth ſundry <hi>Objections</hi> againſt it, and ſheweth at large <hi>what great good there is in children's Memberſhip.</hi> In which Diſcourſes he aſſerteth, <hi>That as they are Members in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, ſo they continue Members when they are grown up, till for their wickedneſs they be caſt out; and that they being Members, their ſeed ſucceſſively are Members alſo, until by Diſſolution or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication they be unchurched: That though they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, it follows not that they muſt come to the Lords Supper, but they muſt firſt appear able to examine themſelves, and diſcern the Lords Body: That the children of godly parents, though they do not manifeſt faith in the Goſpel, yet they are to be accounted of Gods Church, until they poſitively reject the Goſpel,</hi> Rom. <hi>11. That this Memberſhip of children hath no tendency in it to pollute the Church, no more then in the Old Teſtament, but is a means rather of the contrary; And that there is as much danger (if not more) of the degenerating and apoſtatizing of Churches gathered of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Believers, as of thoſe that riſe out of the ſeed of ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prudden</hi> in a Letter to a friend written in the year <hi>1651.</hi> doth plainly expreſs it to be his judgement, <hi>That the children of Church-members, are Members, and ſo have right to have their children baptized though themſelves be not yet admitted to the Lords Supper.</hi> His words are theſe: <hi>Touching the deſire of ſuch Members chidren as deſire to have their children baptized, it is a thing that I do not yet hear practiſed in any of our Churches But for my own part, I am inclined to think, that it cannot juſtly be denied, becauſe their next Parents (however not admitted to the Lords Supper) ſtand as compleat Members of the Church, within the Church Covenant, and ſo acknowledged that they might have right to Baptiſm Now they being in Covenant, and ſtanding Members, their Children alſo are Members by virtue of their Parents Covenant and Memberſhip, as well as they themſelves were by virtue of their Parents Covenant and Memberſhip; And they have not renounced that Covenant, nor are juſtly cenſured for breach of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but do own it and profeſs, it, and by virtue of it claim the priviledge of it to their Children.</hi> Then he puts this his Argument into form thus: <hi>Thoſe Children who are within the Covenant of the Curch, and ſo Membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of it, Baptiſm cannot be denied unto. But the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dren in queſtion are within the Covenant of the Church, and ſo Members of it. Therefore Baptiſm cannot be denied unto them. The Aſſumption is proved thus: The
<pb facs="tcp:94891:7"/>Children of ſuch Parents as are within the Covenant of the Church, and ſo Members of the Church, are themſelves within the Covenant of the Church, and ſo Members of it. But the Children in queſtion are Children of ſuch Parents as are in Covenant, and ſo Members of the Church. Therefore they are ſo themſelves. The Propoſition is clear, becauſe the Parents Covenant for themſelves, and for their Children,</hi> Deut. <hi>29.10,-16.</hi> Ezek. <hi>16.8, 13. And God accepts both,</hi> Gen. <hi>17.12, 13. the whole Nation is foederally holy,</hi> Ezra <hi>9.2. they are expreſly ſaid to be in Covenant with their fathers,</hi> Deut <hi>29. not partly or partially in Covenant,</hi> Rom. <hi>9.3, 4.</hi> Acts <hi>2.39. and God ſtyles himſelf their God as well as their fathers,</hi> Gen. <hi>17.7, 8, 9. and to have God to be our God, is to be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Church Covenant with him. The Aſſumption is evident, becauſe elſe ſuch their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had not had right to Baptiſm the Seal of the Covenant, but that they had right unto, and ſo received it; and the ſame right that they had, their Children have, who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in their Covenant, as they were in their fathers— and are not leſs truely or leſs compleatly in Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, (to adde no more) Mr. <hi>Nath. Rogers,</hi> in a Letter to a Friend, bearing date <hi>18.11. 1652.</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>To the Queſtion concerning the Children of Church-members, I have nothing to oppoſe, and I wonder any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ould deny them to be Members. They are Members</hi> in cenſu Eccleſiaſtice; <hi>God ſo calls them, the Church is ſo to account of them: And when they are</hi> adultae aetatis, <hi>though having done no perſonal act, yet are to be in Charity judged Members ſtill, and till after due calling upon, they ſhall refuſe or neglect to acknowledge and own the Covenant of their Parents, and profeſs their belief of, and ſubjection to the contents thereof— <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ot Practiſe, I confeſs I account it our great default, that we have made no more real diſtinction between theſe and others, that they have been no more attended, as the lambs of the Flock of Chriſt: and whether it be not the cauſe of the corruption and woeful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of our youth,</hi> diſquiri permittimus.</p>
            <p>So that it was the judgement of theſe Worthies in their time, that the children of Church-members are members of the Church as well as their parents, and do not ceaſe to be members by becoming adult, but do ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Church, untill in ſome way of God they be caſt out; and that they are ſubject to Church-diſcipline, even as other members, and may have their children baptized before themſelves be received to the Lords Supper: and yet that in this way there is no tendency to the corrupting of the Church by unworthy members, or of the Ordinances by unworthy partakers. And in the <hi>Synod</hi> herd at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in the year <hi>1648.</hi> that particular point of Baptizing the children of ſuch as were admitted members in minority, but not yet in full communion, was inſerted in ſome of the draughts that were prepared for that Aſſembly, and was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and confirmed by the like Arguments as we now uſe, and was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conſented to; though becauſe ſome few diſſented, and there was not the like urgency of occaſion for preſent practiſe, it was not then put into the <hi>Platform</hi> that was after Printed. We need not mention the <hi>Meeting</hi> of <hi>Elders</hi> at <hi>Boſton</hi> upon the Call of the Honoured <hi>Court</hi> in the year <hi>1657.</hi> where in <hi>Anſwer to XXI. Queſtions,</hi> ſince Printed, this Point is particularly aſſerted. By all which it appeareth, that theſe are not things lately deviſed, or before unheard-of, nor can they juſtly be cenſured
<pb facs="tcp:94891:7"/>as <hi>Innovations</hi> or <hi>Declenſions</hi> from the received Doctrine in <hi>New-England.</hi> It is true, that in the beginning of theſe Plantations, and the Infancy of theſe Churches, there was not ſo much ſaid touching theſe things as there hath been ſince; and the reaſon is, Becauſe then there was not the like occaſion as ſince hath been: Few children of Church-members being then adult, at leaſt few that were then married, and had children. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, when a Queſtion was put about the priviledges of Members children, when come to years, theſe Churches then having been but of few years ſtanding, our Anſwer was, That by reaſon of the Infancy of theſe Churches, we had then had no occaſion to determine what to judge or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in that matter. <hi>Anſwer to the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> and 6<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of 32. Queſtions:</hi> which may ſatisfie as the Reaſon why in our firſt beginnings there was no more ſaid touching theſe Queſtions. But afterwards, when there was more cauſe for it, many of the Elders in theſe Churches, both ſuch as are now living, and ſundry who are now deceaſed, did declare their judgements as aforeſaid, and this many years ago.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Touching Conſociation of Churches, take theſe few Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, in ſtead of many more that might be alledged.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton, Keyes, p. 54, 55. It is a ſafe and wholſome and holy. Ordinance of Chriſt, for particular Churches to joyn together in holy Covenant, or Communion &amp; Conſociation among themſelves, to adminiſter all their Church-affairs (which are of weighty, and difficult and common concernment) not without common conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſent of other Churches about them.</hi> And how it is ſo, he there ſheweth in all the particulars. See alſo <hi>p. 24, 25, 47 59.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hooker, Survey,</hi> ſee <hi>part 4. p. 1, 2. &amp; p. 45.</hi> And in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face he profeſſeth his conſent with Mr. <hi>R. That Conſociation of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is not only lawful, but in ſome caſes neceſſary. That when cauſes are difficult, and particular Churches want light and help they ſhould crave the aſſiſtance of ſuch a Conſociation. That Churches ſo meeting have right to Counſel, Rebuke,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as the caſe doth require. And in caſe any particular Church ſhall walk pertinaciouſly, either in the profeſſion of Errour or ſinful Practiſe, and will not hear their counſel, they may and ſhould renounce the right hand of fellowſhip with them.</hi> And after he ſets down this of <hi>Conſociation of Churches</hi> amongst other things, wherein <hi>he had leave to profeſs the joynt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Elders upon the River; of</hi> New-haven, Guilford, Milford, Stratford, Fairfield, and moſt of the Elders in the Bay. By
<pb facs="tcp:94891:8"/>which it is clear, that this point of Conſociation of Churches is no new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of theſe times, but was taught and profeſſed in <hi>New-England</hi> many years agoe, for ſo it was we ſee in Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s time, and it is now above fifteen years ſince he departed this life.</p>
            <p>To theſe of our own Miniſters, we ſhall only adde a paſſage in the <hi>Apologetical Narration</hi> of Dr. <hi>Goodwyn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Nye,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sidrach Simpſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burroughes,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bridge;</hi> wherein, beſides much more to this purpoſe, touching the Remedy provided in the Congregational-way for mal-Adminiſtrations, or other miſcarriages in Churches, <hi>p. 16-21.</hi> They ſet it down (in <hi>p. 27.</hi>) as their paſt and preſent Profeſſion, <hi>That it</hi> is <hi>the moſt to be abhorred Maxime that any Religion hath ever made profeſſion of, and therefore of all other the moſt contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory and diſhonourable unto that of Chriſtianity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that a ſingle and particular Society of men, profeſſing the Name of Chriſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be endowed with a Power from Chriſt, to judge them that are of the ſame Body and Society within themſelves, ſhould further arrogate unto themſelves an exemption from giving account, or being cenſurable by any other, either Chriſtian Magiſtrate above them, or Neighbour-Churches about them.</hi> See alſo Mr. <hi>Burroughes Heart-Diviſ. pag 43, 47.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Brethren, bear with us: Were it for our own: Sakes, or Names, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, we ſhould not be ſollicitous to beg Charity of you. With us <hi>it is a ſmall thing to be judged of man's day.</hi> But it is for your ſakes, for your children's ſake, and for the Lord's ſake, that we intreat for a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, candid, and conſiderate Acceptation of our labour herein. It is that the <hi>Congregations</hi> of the Lord might be <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> before Him in <hi>Truth and Peace,</hi> and that they might have <hi>one heart and one way</hi> in the fear of God, <hi>for the good of them and of their children after them.</hi> Do we herein ſeek our ſelves? our own advantage, eaſe or glory? Surely we feel the contrary! What is it we deſire, but that we might do our utmoſt to carry your poor Children to Heaven; and that we might ſee theſe Churches bound up together in the Bonds of Truth and Peace? <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us this wrong.</hi> But ſhould the Church-education of your children be by the want of your hearty concurrence, rendred either unfeizible or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual; ſhould they live as <hi>Lambs in a large place,</hi> for want of your agreement to own them <hi>of the Flock,</hi> we beſeech you to conſider how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable the account hereof would be another day. We <hi>pray</hi> with the Apoſtle, <hi>that you do no evil, not that we ſhould appear approved,
<pb facs="tcp:94891:8"/>but that you ſhould do that which is</hi> good and right, <hi>though we be rejected. For we can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth: and this alſo we wiſh, even your perfection, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>13.7, 8, 9.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we hope after-ages will bear witneſs, that we have been in ſome meaſure faithful to the Truth in theſe things, and to this part of Chriſts Kingdome alſo in our generation.</p>
            <p>But we may not let paſs this opportunity, without a word of Caution and Exhortation to the <hi>Youth</hi> of the Country, the <hi>children</hi> of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, whoſe Intereſt we have here aſſorted. Be not you puffed up with Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, but humbled rather, in the awful ſenſe of the Engagement, Duty and Danger that doth attend them: It is an high favour to have a place in <hi>Bethel, in the houſe of God, and in the gate of Heaven;</hi> but it is a <hi>Dreadful place:</hi> God will be <hi>ſanctified</hi> in all that <hi>come nigh him.</hi> A place nigh unto God (or among his people who are <hi>near to him, Pſ. 148.14</hi>) is a place of great fear, <hi>Pſa. 89.7. Take heed</hi> therefore unto your ſelves, when owned as <hi>the people of the Lord your God,</hi> (Deut. <hi>27.9, 10.</hi>) <hi>leſt there ſhould be among you any root that beareth gall and worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</hi> Take heed that you do not with a ſpirit of pride and haughtineſs, or of vanity and ſlightneſs, either challenge or uſe any of your Priviledges. Think not to bear the Name of Chriſtians, without bearing the Yoke of Chriſt. Remember, that all Relations to God and to his people, do come loaden with <hi>Duty;</hi> and all Goſpel-duty muſt be done in <hi>humility.</hi> The wayes of the Lord are right, and the humble and ſerious ſhall walk in them, but proud Tranſgreſſors ſhall fall therein. Be not <hi>ſons of Belial,</hi> that can bear no yoke: Learn ſubjection to Chriſts holy Government in all the parts and wayes thereof. Be ſubject to your godly Parents: Be ſubject to your spirtiual Fathers and Paſtors, and to all their inſtructions, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and Exhortations: Be ſubject unto faithful Brethren, and to words of counſel and help from them: <hi>Ye younger, ſubmit your ſelves unto the elder;</hi> and to that end, <hi>be clothed with humility.</hi> Lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Word and Will of Chriſt, as diſpenſed and conveyed to you by all his appointed Inſtruments in their reſpective places. Break not in upon the Lord's Table (or upon the Priviledges of full Communion) without due qualification, and orderly admiſſion thereunto, leſt you <hi>eat and drink your own damnation</hi> Be ordered, and take not upon you to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the affairs of Gods Family; that is not the place of thoſe who are yet but in the ſtate of Initiation and Education in the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch of God. Carry it in all things with a spirit of humility, modeſty, ſobriety and
<pb facs="tcp:94891:9"/>fear, that our ſoules may not weep in ſecret for your <hi>pride,</hi> and that God may not <hi>reſiſt</hi> &amp; <hi>reject</hi> you as a generation of his wrath. Oh that the Lord would pour out a spirit of Humiliation &amp; Repentance upon all the younger ſort in the Country, (yea &amp; upon elder too, for our neglects) from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba!</hi> Oh that we might meet at <hi>Bochim,</hi> becauſe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Canaanues of unſubdued, yea growing corruptions are found among us! Let it not be ſaid, that when the firſt &amp; beſt generation in New-England were <hi>gathered to their fathers, there aroſe another generation after them that knew not the Lord.</hi> Behold, the <hi>Lord had a delight in your fathers to love them,</hi> and he hath choſen you <hi>their ſeed after them,</hi> to enjoy theſe Liberties &amp; Opportunities, as it is this day: <hi>Circumciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fore-skin of your hearts, and be no more ſtiff-necked,</hi> but <hi>yield your ſelves to the Lord,</hi> and to the Order of <hi>His Sanctuary,</hi> to ſeek him, and wait on him in all his wayes with holy fear and trembling: for the Lord your God is gracious and merciful, and will not turn away his face from you, if you return unto him; if you ſeek him he will be found of you, but if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you forſake him, he will caſt you off for ever.</p>
            <p>We ſhall conclude, when we have given the Reader a ſhort account of the Work enſuing. The <hi>Propoſitions</hi> in Anſwer to the <hi>firſt Queſtion,</hi> were (after much diſcuſſion and conſideration from the Word of God) Voted and Concluded by the Aſſembly in <hi>the particular terms</hi> as they are here expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The <hi>Arguments</hi> then uſed for their <hi>Confirmation,</hi> being drawn up by ſome deputed thereunto, after they had been ſeveral times read and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the Aſſembly, were Voted and Conſented to, <hi>as to the ſumme and ſubſtance</hi> thereof. The Anſwer to the <hi>ſecond Queſtion</hi> is here given with great brevity, partly becauſe ſo much is already ſaid there-about in the foreſaid <hi>Platform of Diſcipline,</hi> and partly by reaſon of great ſtraits of time: But what is here preſented was the <hi>joynt concluſion</hi> of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. A <hi>Preface</hi> was deſired by the Aſſembly to be prefixed by ſome appointed thereunto, which is here accordingly by them performed.</p>
            <p>Now the God of truth &amp; peace guide us &amp; all his people in the wayes, &amp; give us the fruits thereof; help us to <hi>feed</hi> his flock and his lambs, &amp; to be <hi>fed</hi> by him as the ſheep of his paſture, that when the <hi>chief-Shepherd ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</hi> we may <hi>receive</hi> together <hi>a Crown of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> &amp; may enter into the joy of our Lord, as thoſe that have neither deſpiſed his <hi>little ones,</hi> nor denied to be our <hi>Brother's keeper:</hi> But having faithfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured to promote the continuation of his Kingdom, &amp; Communion of his people, may Reſt &amp; Reign with all Saints in the kingdom of his glory. <hi>Unto whom be glory in the Church by Chriſt Jeſus throughout all ages world without end.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94891:9"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER OF THE ELDERS AND OTHER MESSENGERS of the Churches, Aſſembled at Boſton in the Year 1662. TO The Queſtions Propounded to them by ORDER of the Honoured GENERAL COURT.</head>
            <p>Queſt, 1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho are the Subjects of Baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw: The Anſwer</hi> may be given in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing propoſitions, briefly confirmed from the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>They that according to Scripture, are Members of the Viſible Church, are the ſubjects of Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The Members of the Viſible Church according to ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are Confederate viſible Believers, in particular Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and their infant-ſeed.</hi> i. e. <hi>children in minority, whoſe next parents, one or both, are in Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>The Infant-ſeed of confederate viſible Believers, are members of the ſame Church with their parents, and when grown up, are perſonally under the watch, diſcipline and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Theſe Adult perſons, are not therefore to be admitted to full Communion, meerly becauſe they are and continue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94891:10"/>members, without ſuch further qualifications, as the Word of God requireth therunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Church-members who were admitted in minority, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Doctrine of Faith, and publickly profeſſing their aſſent thereto; not ſcandalous in life, and ſolemnly owning the Covenant before the Church, wherin they give up themſelves and their children to the Lord, and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Christ in the Church, their children are to be Baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Such Church-members, who either by death, or ſome other extraordinary Providence, have been inevitably hindred from publick acting as aforeſaid, yet have given the Church cauſe in judgment of charity, to look at them as ſo qualified, and ſuch as had they been called thereunto, would have ſo acted, their children are to be Baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>The members of Orthodox Churches, being found in the Faith, and not ſcandalous in life, and preſenting due teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof; theſe occaſionally comming from one Church to another, may have their children Baptiſed in the church wither they come, by virtue of communion of churches: but if they remove their habitation, they ought orderly to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Chriſt in the church where they ſettle their abode, and ſo their children to be Baptiſed. It being the churches duty to receive ſuch unto communion, ſo farr as they are regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Confirmation of theſe Propoſitions from the Scripture followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition First.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>They that according to Scripture are members of the viſible Church, are the ſubjects of Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The trueth hereof may appear by the following evidences from the word of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Go ye therefore and</hi> teach, or (as the Greek is) <hi>diſciple all Nations, Baptiſing them, Mat.</hi> 28.19
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94891:10"/>he expreſſeth the adequate ſubject of Baptiſme, to be <hi>diſciples,</hi> or <hi>diſcipled ones.</hi> But <hi>diſciples</hi> there is the ſame with <hi>members of the viſible church:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the viſible Church is Chriſts <hi>ſchool,</hi> wherein all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſtand related and ſubjected to him, as their Maſter and Teacher, and ſo are his <hi>ſcholars</hi> or <hi>diſciples,</hi> and under his teaching, as <hi>verſe</hi> 20. And it is that viſible ſpiritual Kingdome of Chriſt, which he there from his Kingly power, <hi>ver:</hi> 18. ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to ſet up and adminiſter in <hi>ver:</hi> 19. the ſubjects where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are under his Lawes and Government: <hi>verſe</hi> 20. Which ſubjects (or members of that Kingdome <hi>i.e.</hi> of the viſible church) are termed diſciples <hi>verſe</hi> 19. Alſo in the Acts of the Apoſtles (the ſtory of their accompliſhment of that commiſſion) <hi>diſciples</hi> are uſually put for <hi>members of the viſible church: Acts</hi> 1.15 <hi>In the mids of the diſciples:</hi> who with others added to them, are called <hi>the church, Acts</hi> 2: 47: The members whereof are again called <hi>diſciples, Acts</hi> 6: 1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 9; 1, — <hi>againſt the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Lord,</hi> i.e againſt <hi>the church of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 9 <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13 <hi>Acts</hi> 9 26 <hi>He aſſayed to joyn himſelf to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. The diſciples at Lyſtra, Iconiem and Antioch,</hi> Acts 14 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 22 are called <hi>the church</hi> in each of thoſe places <hi>verſe</hi> 23 So <hi>the church verſe</hi> 27 <hi>the diſciples verſe</hi> 28. Acts 18.22 <hi>the church at Ceſarea;</hi> Acts 21.16 the <hi>diſciples of Ceſarea:</hi> So Acts 18 23 with <hi>chap.</hi> 15.41. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2. Acts 18.27 and <hi>chap.</hi> 20 1 with <hi>verſe</hi> 17.28. From all which it appeareth that <hi>diſciples</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19 and <hi>members of the viſible church,</hi> are termes equivalent: and <hi>diſciples</hi> being there by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe made the ſubjects of Baptiſm, it follows that the members of the viſible Church are the ſubjects of baptiſme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Baptiſm is <hi>the ſeal of first entrance or admiſſion into the viſible church;</hi> as appeareth from thoſe texts 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12: 13. <hi>Baptiſed into one body,</hi> i e. our entrance into the body or church of Chriſt, is ſealed by Baptiſme: and <hi>Rom;</hi> 6 3, 5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3: 27. where it is ſhewed that Baptiſme is the Sacrament of <hi>union</hi> or of <hi>ingrafting</hi> into Chriſt the head, and conſequently into the church his body &amp; from the Apoſtles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant practiſe in baptiſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94891:11"/>perſons upon their firſt comming in, or firſt giving up themſelves to the Lord and them. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.15, 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.8. and in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41, 42. they were baptized at their firſt <hi>adding</hi> to the church, or admiſſion into the <hi>Apoſtles fellowſhip,</hi> wherin they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>continued.</hi> And from its anſwering unto circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, which was a ſeal of initiation or admiſſion into the church; Hence it belongs to all and onely thoſe that are entred into, that are within, or that are members of the viſible church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>They that according to Scripture are members of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, they are in Corenant.</hi> For it is the Covenant that conſtituteth the Church, <hi>Deut</hi> 29.12, 13. They muſt <hi>enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to covenant,</hi> that they might be <hi>eſtabliſhed the people</hi> or Church <hi>of God.</hi> Now the initiatory ſeal is affixed to the Covenant and appointed to run parallel therewith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 9, 10, 11. ſo circumciſion was: and hence called <hi>the covenant Gen.</hi> 17.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.8. and ſo Baptiſme is, being in like manner annexed to <hi>the promiſe</hi> or Covenant, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. and being the ſeal that anſwereth to circumciſion; <hi>Col:</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Chriſt doth Sanctifie and cleanſe the Church by the waſhing of water, i e,</hi> by Baptiſme <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.26 Therefore the whole Church and ſo all the members thereof (who are alſo ſaid in Scripture to be <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.2.) are the ſubjects of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: And although it is the <hi>inviſible church,</hi> unto the ſpiritual and eternall good whereof, this and all other Ordinances laſtly have reſpect, and which the place mentioned in <hi>Eph:</hi> 5. may in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er look unto, yet it is <hi>the viſible Church</hi> that is the next and immediate ſubject of the adminiſtration thereof.</p>
            <p>For the ſubject of viſible external ordinances to be adminiſtred by men, muſt needs be viſible. And ſo the Apoſtles Baptized ſundry perſons, who were of the viſible, but not of the inviſible Church, as Simon Magus, Anamias and Sapphira, and others.</p>
            <p>And theſe are viſibly <hi>Purchaſed</hi> and <hi>Sanctified</hi> by the bloud of Chriſt, <hi>the Bloud of the covenant, Acts</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.28. <hi>Heb</hi> 10.29. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the viſible ſeal of the covenant and of cleanſing by Chriſts bloud belongs to them.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94891:11"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The Circumciſion is often put for the whole Jewiſh Church or for the members of the viſible Church under the Old Teſtament.</hi> Thoſe within are expreſſed by <hi>[the circumciſed]</hi> and thoſe without by <hi>[the uncircumciſed.] Rom:</hi> 15.8. &amp; 3.30. <hi>Eph:</hi> 2, 11. <hi>Judg:</hi> 14.3. &amp; 15.18. 1 <hi>San:</hi> 14.6 &amp; 17.26, 36. <hi>Jer</hi> 9, 25, 26. Hence by proportion Baptiſme (which is our Goſpel circumciſion, Col: 2.11.12.) belongs to the whole viſible Church under the new Teſtament. Actual and perſonal circumciſion was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed proper to the males of old, females being but incluſively and virtually circumciſed, and ſo counted of the circumciſion: but the Lord hath taken away that difference now, and appointed Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to be perſonally applied to both ſexes: <hi>Act:</hi> 8.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.15. <hi>Gal:</hi> 3 28. So that every particular member of the viſible Church is now a ſubject of Baptiſme. We conclude therefore that Baptiſme pertaines to the whole viſible Church, and to all and every one therein, and to no other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition</hi> 2d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The members of the viſible Church according to Scripture, are confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate viſible believers, in particular Churches, and their infant-ſeed,</hi> i, e, <hi>children in minority, whoſe next parents, one or both, are in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sundry particulars are compriſed in this propoſition, which wee may conſider and confirme diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adult perſons who are members of the viſible Church,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic: </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>are by rule confederate viſible beleevers: Acts:</hi> 5.14. <hi>believers were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Lord</hi> The <hi>believing</hi> Corinthians were members of the Church there <hi>Acts</hi> 18: 8 <hi>with</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 1.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.27. The inſcriptions of the Epiſtles written to Churches, and calling the members thereof <hi>Sants,</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> ſhew the ſame thing, <hi>Eph</hi> 1.1. <hi>Phi</hi> 1.1. <hi>Col,</hi> 1.2. And that conſederation, <hi>i, e.</hi> covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing explicite or implicite, [the latter preſerveth the eſſence of confederation the former is duety and moſt deſireable) is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to make one a member of the viſible Church, appears. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church is conſtituted by Covenant: for there is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94891:12"/>between Chriſt and the Church the mutuall engagement and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of King and ſubjects, husband and ſpouſe; this cannot be but by Covenant (internall, if you ſpeak of the inviſible Church, external of the viſible) a church is a company that can ſay, God is our God and we are his people, this is from the covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them. <hi>Deut</hi> 29, 12, 13, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 16, 8. 3. The church of the old Teſtament was the church of God <hi>by covenant Gen</hi> 17, <hi>Deut</hi> 29 and was reformed ſtill by renewing of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant 2 <hi>chron</hi> 15, 12. &amp; 23, 16: <hi>&amp;</hi> 34, 31 32 <hi>Neh:</hi> 9 38: Now the churches of the Gentiles under the new Teſtament ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame baſis or <hi>root</hi> with the church of the Old Teſtament, &amp; therefore are conſtituted by <hi>Covenant,</hi> as that was <hi>Rom:</hi> 11.17.18. <hi>Eph:</hi> 2 11, 12, 19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3: 6. <hi>Heb:</hi> 8: 10, 3. Baptiſme enters us into the Church Sacramentally, <hi>i, e,</hi> by ſealing the Covenant. The <hi>Covenant</hi> therefore is that which conſtitutes the Church and inferrs memberſhip, and is the <hi>Vow</hi> in <hi>Baptiſme</hi> commonly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The members of the viſible Church are ſuch as are confederate in Particular Churches.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic: </seg>2</label> It may be minded that we are here ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Members ſo ſtated in the viſible Church, as that they are Subjects to whom Church ordinances may regularly be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and that according to ordinary diſpenſation. For were it graunted that <hi>the Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> did ſometimes Baptize ſuch, as were not Members of any Particular Church, yet their extraordinary office, large Power and commiſſion renders them not imitable therein by <hi>ordinary Officers.</hi> For then they might Baptize in private without the preſence of a Chriſtian aſſemblie, as <hi>Philip did the Eunuch.</hi> But that in ordinary diſpenſation the Members of the viſible Church according to Scripture, are ſuch as are Members of ſome particular Church, appeares, 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the viſible beleever that profeſſedly Covenants with God, doth therein give up himſelfe to wait on God in all his ordinances. <hi>Deut</hi> 26: 17, 18. <hi>Math:</hi> 28, 19, 20. But all the Ordinances of God are to be enjoyed onely in a particular Church. For how often do we find in the Scripture that they came <hi>together into one place</hi> (or met as a congregational particular Church) for the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and enjoyment of the Ordinances <hi>Acts:</hi> 2: 1, 44, 46.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94891:12"/>
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 4, 31: <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20: 7. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 5: 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.18.20: 33 <hi>&amp;</hi> 14: 23. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 2. The Apoſtle in his Epiſtles writing to <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Beleevers,</hi> writes to them as in <hi>particular Churches.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 1: 2. <hi>Eph:</hi> 1. 1. <hi>Phil:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: 1. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. And when the ſtory of the Acts ſpeakes of Diſciples other places ſhew that thoſe are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be <hi>Members of particular Churches, Acts</hi> 18.23. <hi>with</hi> Gal: 1: 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 21 16. <hi>with Chap</hi> 18: 22 <hi>Acts:</hi> 11.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14: 22, 23,27,28. All which ſhewes that the Scripture acknowledgeth no ſettled orderly eſtate of viſible beleevers in Covenant with God, but onely in particular Churches. 3. The members of the viſible Church are Diſciples, as was above cleared: now <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> are under <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and liable to Church-cenſures: for they are ſtated ſubjects of Chriſts Laws and Government, <hi>Mar:</hi> 28.19, 20. but Church Government and cenſures are extant now in ordinary diſpenſation, onely in a particular Church. <hi>Mat</hi> 18.17. 1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Infant-ſeed of confederate viſible beleevers are alſo members of the viſible Church,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic: </seg>3</label> The truth of this is evident from the Scriptures and reaſons following.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>The covenant of Abraham as to the ſubſtance thereof,</hi> viz, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>that whereby God declares himſelfe to be the God of the faithfull &amp; their ſeed, Gen:</hi> 17.7. <hi>continues under the Goſpel,</hi> as appears. 1 Becauſe the Beleeving inchurched <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the new Teſtament, do ſtand upon the ſame <hi>root</hi> of <hi>covenanting Abraham;</hi> which the <hi>Jewes</hi> were <hi>broken off from, Rom</hi> 11, 16, 17 18. 2 Becauſe Abraham in regard of that Covenant was made a <hi>Father of many nations, Gen:</hi> 17.4, 5. even of Gentiles as well as Jewes, under New-Teſtament as well as Old, <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.16 17. <hi>Gal</hi> 3, 29, <hi>i, e,</hi> in Abraham as a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and root, God (not onely ſhewed how he Juſtifies the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3, 6, 9. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4. but alſo) conveied that covenant to the faithfull and their ſeed in all nations, <hi>Luk:</hi> 19.9. If a Son: of Abraham, then <hi>Salvation, i, e:</hi> the Covenant-diſpenſation of Salvation is <hi>come to his houſe.</hi> 3. As that covenant was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to proſelyte Gentiles under the Old Teſtament, ſo its communication to the inchurched Gentiles under the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is clearly heldforth in diverſe places <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.14 the bleſſing of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94891:13"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> comprizeth both the internal benefits of Juſtification by faith &amp;c which the Apoſtle is there treating of; and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal diſpenſation of Grace in the viſible church to the faithfull &amp; their ſeed, <hi>Gen:</hi> 28 4. but the whole Bleſſing of Abraham, and ſo the whole covenant) <hi>is come upon the Genitles through Jeſus Chriſt. Eph:</hi> 2.12, 19 They had been <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> but now were <hi>no more strangers</hi> from <hi>the covenants of promiſe i, e,</hi> from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, which had been often renewed, eſpecially with Abraham and the houſe of Iſrael, and had been in the externall diſpenſation of it, their peculiar portion, ſo that the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> who were a farr off, being now called and made nigh, <hi>v.</hi> 13-17. they have the promiſe or the Covenant of promiſe to them and to their Children, according to <hi>Acts:</hi> 2, 39. and ſo are partakers of that Covenant of Abraham, that we are ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eph:</hi> 3,6. The inchurched Gentiles are put into the ſame <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> for ſubſtance (both as to inviſible &amp; viſible benefits accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their reſpective conditions) are of the <hi>ſame body,</hi> and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſame promiſe</hi> with the Jewes, the Children of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, of old. The ſame may be gathered from <hi>Gen:</hi> 9, 27. <hi>Mat</hi> 8 11, <hi>&amp;</hi> 21, 43.4. Sundry Scriptures which extend to Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-times do confirme the ſame intereſt to the ſeed of the faithful which is held forth in the covenant of Abraham, and conſequently do confirme the continuance of that covenant: as <hi>Exod:</hi> 20: 6. there in the ſanction of a moral and perpetual Commandement, and that reſpecting Ordinances, the portion of the church, God declareth himſelf to be a <hi>God of mercy, to them that love him,</hi> and to their ſeed after them <hi>in their generations:</hi> conſonant to <hi>Gen:</hi> 17.7. compare herewith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.8, 9 <hi>&amp; Deut.</hi> 7.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. The grace ſignified by <hi>circumciſion</hi> is there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Parents and children, importing the covenant to both, which circumciſion ſealed, <hi>Gen:</hi> 17. and that is a Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as the Apoſtles citing part of that context as the voice of the Goſpel, ſhewes <hi>Rom:</hi> 10, 6-8. with <hi>Deut:</hi> 30, 11-14. and it reacheth to the Jewes in the latter dayes, <hi>ver.</hi> 1-5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſay:</hi> 65 23. In the moſt Glorious Goſpel-ſtate of the church, <hi>ver.</hi> 17-19. the bleſſing of the Lord is the promiſed portion of the <hi>off-ſpring</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94891:13"/>or Children, as well as of the faithfull parents ſo <hi>Iſay:</hi> 44.3, 4. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſai:</hi> 59.20, 21. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 37 25, 26. at the future cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Jewes, which thoſe texts have reference to, (<hi>Rom:</hi> 11.26. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 37.19-22, 23 24.) <hi>their Children</hi> ſhall be under the promiſe or Covenant of ſpecial Grace to be conveyed to them in the Ordinances, <hi>Iſai:</hi> 59.21. and be ſubjects of <hi>David, i, e,</hi> Chriſt <hi>their King Ezek</hi> 37.25. and have a portion in his <hi>Sanctuary, verſ</hi> 26. and this according to the tenor of the ancient <hi>covenant</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> whereby God will be <hi>their God</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> both of parents and Children) <hi>and they ſhall be</hi> his <hi>People, verſ:</hi> 26,27. Now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though more abundant fruits of the Covenant may be ſeen in thoſe times, and the Jewes then may have more abundant Grace given to the body of them to continue in the Covenant, yet the tenor and frame of the Covenant itſelfe is one and the ſame, both to Jewes, and Gentiles under the New-Teſtament; <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.28, <hi>Coll:</hi> 3.11. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. <hi>The houſe of Iſrael, i, e,</hi> the Church of <hi>God</hi> both among <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the new Teſtament, have that Covenant made with them, the ſumm whereof is, <hi>I will be their God and they ſhall be my people:</hi> which is a renewing of that Covenant of <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Gen</hi> 17. (as the ſame is very often over in thoſe termes renewed in Scripture, and is diſtinguiſhed from the Law, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3 16, 17. <hi>Heb</hi> 8.9) wherein is implied Gods being <hi>a God to the ſeed</hi> as well as parents, and taking <hi>both</hi> to be his <hi>People,</hi> though it be not expreſſed: even as it is often plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implied in that expreſſion of the Covenant in other places of Scripture: <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.38, 39, <hi>&amp;</hi> 24: 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30 22, 20. <hi>Ezek:</hi> 37.27, 25. Alſo the <hi>writing of the Law in the heart,</hi> in <hi>Heb:</hi> 8: 10. is that <hi>heart circumciſion</hi> which <hi>Deut:</hi> 30 6. extends both to parents and ſeed. And the terme, <hi>Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> doth according to Scripture-uſe fitly expreſse and take in (eſpecially as to the externall adminiſtration of the Covenant) both parents and Children: among both which are found that elect and ſaved number, that make up the inviſible Iſrael compare <hi>Jer:</hi> 13.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.26. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5 7. <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 1.6 <hi>Ezk:</hi> 39.25. Neither may we exclude the <hi>leaſt in age</hi> from the good of that promiſe, <hi>Heb</hi> 8: 11, (they being ſometimes pointed to by that phraſe, <hi>from the leaſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94891:14"/>to the greateſt, Jer.</hi> 44.12. with <hi>verſe</hi> 7.) no more then the leaſt in other reſpects; compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. at the paſſing of thoſe Jews into New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Church eſtate, the Lord is ſo far from <hi>repealing the Covenant-intereſt</hi> that was granted unto <hi>children</hi> in the former Teſtament, or from making the children there loſers by their Parents faith, that he doth expreſly <hi>renew</hi> the old grant, and tells them that <hi>the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> or covenant (for the promiſe and the covenant are terms that do mutually infer each other; compare <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16, 17, 18, 29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6 17) <hi>is to them and to their children:</hi> and the ſame is aſſerted to be the appointed portion of <hi>the far off</hi> Gentiles, when they ſhould be <hi>called.</hi> By all which it appeareth, that the <hi>covenant of Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. <hi>whereby God is the God of the faithfull and their ſeed, continues under the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the ſeed of the faithful be ſtill in the covenant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> then <hi>they are members of the viſible Church;</hi> 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that covenant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17.7. was properly <hi>church-covenant,</hi> or <hi>the covenant which God makes with his viſible church, i. e.</hi> the covenant of grace conſidered in the external diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and in the promiſes and priviledges that belong to that diſpenſation. For many were taken into that covenant, that were never of the <hi>inviſible</hi> church: and by that covenant, the family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as alſo by the renewing thereof, the houſe of Iſrael af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward were eſtabliſhed the viſible church of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 29 12, 13. and from that covenant men might be broken off, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17: 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17, 19. and to that covenant, <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the badg of church-memberſhip, was annexed. Therefore the covenantees therein were &amp; are church-members. 2. Becauſe in that covenant, the ſeed are ſpoken of in terms deſcribing or inferring church-memberſhip, as well as their parents: for they <hi>have God for their God,</hi> and are his <hi>people,</hi> as well as the parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 7, 8. with <hi>Deut:</hi> 29: 11, 13. They have the covenant made <hi>with them,</hi> Deut 29: 14, 15. and the covenant is ſaid to be <hi>between God &amp; them</hi> (<hi>between me &amp; thee, and between thy ſeed after thee:</hi> ſo the Hebrew runs) <hi>Gen:</hi> 17: 7. They are alſo in that covenant appointed to be the ſubjects of the <hi>initiatory ſeal</hi> of the covenant,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94891:14"/>the ſeal of memberſhip, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17: 9, 10, 11. Therefore the ſeed are according to that covenant, members of the viſible church, as well as their parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such ſeed or children are federally holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>2</label> The word <hi>[holy]</hi> as applied to any ſort of perſons, is never in Scripture uſed in a lower ſenſe than for <hi>federal</hi> or <hi>covenant-holineſs,</hi> (the covenant-holineſs of the viſible Church;) but very often in that ſenſe, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9: 2. <hi>Deut:</hi> 7: 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14: 2, 21: <hi>&amp;</hi> 26: 19: <hi>&amp;</hi> 28: 9: <hi>Exod:</hi> 19: 6: <hi>Dan:</hi> 8: 24: <hi>&amp;</hi> 12: 7: <hi>Rom:</hi> 11: 16: So that to ſay they are <hi>holy</hi> in this ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> by covenant-relation and ſeparation to God in his Church, is as much as to ſay, <hi>they are in the covenant of the viſible church, or members of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>Mark</hi> 10: 14, 15, 16: <hi>Mat</hi> 19: 14: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>3</label> childrens memberſhip in the viſible Church, is either the next and immediate ſenſe of thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Of ſuch is the kingdome of heaven;</hi> and ſo <hi>the kingdome of heaver, or of God,</hi> is not rarely uſed in other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to expreſs the viſible church, or church-eſtate, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25: 1: <hi>&amp;</hi> 21: 43: <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.11, 12: or it evidently follows from any other ſenſe that can rationally be given of the words. For thoſe may not be denied a place and portion in the <hi>viſible church,</hi> whom Chriſt affirms to have a portion in the <hi>kingdome</hi> either of <hi>inviſible grace,</hi> or of <hi>eternal glory:</hi> Nor do any in ordinary courſe paſs into the Kingdome of Glory hereafter, but through the Kingdome of Grace in the viſible Church here. Adde alſo, that Chriſt there graciouſly invites and calls <hi>little children</hi> to him, is <hi>greatly diſpleaſed</hi> with thoſe that would hinder them, aſſerts them, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their infancy, to be exemplary in <hi>receiving the kingdome of God,</hi> embraceth them <hi>in his arms,</hi> and <hi>bleſſeth them:</hi> all which ſhews Chriſt's dear affection to, and owning of the children of the Church, as a part of his kingdome; whom we therefore may not diſown, leſt we incurre his diſpleaſure, as the Diſciples did.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such ſeed or children are diſciples according to</hi> Mat 28: 19: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>4</label> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, 1. Becauſe ſubjects of Chriſt's Kingdome are equivalent with diſciples there, as the frame of that Text ſhews, <hi>verſe</hi> 18, 19, 20. but ſuch children are ſubjects of Chriſt's Kingdome, or <hi>of the kingdome of heaven, Mat:</hi> 19: 14: In the diſcipling of all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94891:15"/>Nations intended in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>the kingdome of God,</hi> which had been the portion of the Jews, was communicated to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. But in <hi>the kingdome of God</hi> theſe children have an intereſt or portion, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14. 2. The Apoſtles in accompliſhing that commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. did <hi>diſciple</hi> ſome children, <hi>viz.</hi> the children of diſcipled parents, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.10. They are there called and accounted <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> whom the falſe teachers would have brought under <hi>the yoke of circumciſion after the manner of Moſes, verſe</hi> 1, 5. But many of thoſe were children; <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Acts</hi> 21.21. <hi>Lydia</hi> and <hi>her houſhold,</hi> the Jaylor and <hi>all his,</hi> were diſcipled and bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 31 33. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Corinth</hi> took in the children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>holy ſchool of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor 7.14. 3. Such children <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Chriſt;</hi> for he calls them to him as his, to receive his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.13-16. They are to be received in his Name, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 9 48. They have <hi>a part in the Lord, Joſt.</hi> 22.24.25. therefore they are <hi>diſciples:</hi> for to <hi>belong to Chriſt,</hi> is to be <hi>a diſciple of Chriſt, Mark</hi> 9.41. with <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42. Now if they be diſciples, then they are <hi>members of the viſible church,</hi> as from the equivalency of thoſe terms was before ſhewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The whole current and harmony of Scripture ſhews,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>that ever ſince there was a viſible church on earth, the children thereof have by the Lords appointment been a part of it.</hi> So it was in the Old, and it is and ſhall be ſo in the New Teſtament. <hi>Eve, the mother of all living,</hi> hath a <hi>promiſe</hi> made <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. not only of Chriſt the <hi>head-ſeed,</hi> but through him alſo of a <hi>Church-ſeed,</hi> to proceed from her in a continued lineal ſucceſſion, which ſhould continually be at viſible <hi>enmity with,</hi> and ſtand at a diſtance, or be ſeparated from <hi>the ſeed of the Serpent.</hi> Under that promiſe made to <hi>Eve</hi> and her ſeed, the children of <hi>Adam</hi> are born, and are a part of the Church in <hi>Adam</hi>'s family: even <hi>Cain</hi> was ſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.1, 3. till <hi>caſt out of the preſence of God</hi> therein, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. being now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly one of the ſeed of the Serpent, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. and ſo becoming the father of a wicked unchurched race. Burthen God <hi>appointed</hi> unto <hi>Eve another,</hi> viz: <hi>Seth,</hi> in whom to continue the line of her <hi>Church-ſeed,</hi> Gen 4.25. How it did continue in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94891:15"/>his ſeed <hi>in their generations, Geneſ:</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſheweth. Hence the children of the Church are called <hi>Sons of God,</hi> (which is as much as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the viſible Church) in contradiſtinction to <hi>the daughters of men, Gen.</hi> 6 2. If <hi>righteous Noah</hi> be taken into the <hi>Ark</hi> (then the onely preſerving place of the Church) his <hi>children</hi> are taken in with him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1. though one of them, <hi>viz. Ham,</hi> after proved degenerate and wicked; but till he ſo appears, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Church with his Brethren: So <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25, 26, 27. as the race of <hi>Ham</hi> or his ſon <hi>Canaan</hi> (parent and children) are <hi>curſed;</hi> ſo <hi>Shem</hi> (parent and children) <hi>is bleſſed,</hi> and continued in the place of bleſſing, the Church: As <hi>Japhet</hi> alſo, or <hi>Iaphet</hi>'s poſterity (ſtill parent and children) ſhall in time be brought in. The holy line mentioned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.10-26 ſhews how the Church continued in <hi>the ſeed of Shem</hi> from him unto <hi>Abraham.</hi> When that race grew degenerate, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.2. then God called <hi>Abraham</hi> out of his countrey, and from his kindred, and <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed his covenant with him,</hi> which ſtill took in parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 9. So it did after in the houſe of Iſrael, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11, 12, 13. and when any eminent reſtauration or eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is promiſed to the Church, <hi>the children</hi> thereof are ſtill taken in, as ſharers in the ſame, <hi>Pſal</hi> 102.16, 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 69.35, 36. <hi>Jerem;</hi> 32: 38, 39 <hi>Iſa:</hi> 65: 18, 19, 23. Now when Chriſt comes to ſet up the Goſpel-adminiſtration of his Church in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under the term of <hi>the kingdome of heaven, Mat:</hi> 3: 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.11. he is ſo far from taking away children's portion and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip therein, that himſelf aſſerts it, <hi>Mat:</hi> 19: 14. The <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of the Gentile, but now <hi>believing Corinthians, are holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7: 14. The Apoſtle writing to the Churches of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> ſpeaks to <hi>children,</hi> as a part thereof, <hi>Eph:</hi> 6: 1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3: 20. The inchurched <hi>Romans,</hi> and other <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſtand on the <hi>root of covenanting Abraham,</hi> and in the <hi>Olive</hi> or viſible Church, they and their children, till broken off (as the Jews were) by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive unbelief or rejection of Chriſt, his Truth or Government, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 13, 16, 17,-22. The children of the Jews, when they ſhall be called, ſhall <hi>be as aforetime</hi> in Church-eſtate, <hi>Ie:</hi> 30.20. with 31.1 <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37 25-28 From all which it appears, that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94891:16"/>ſeries or whole frame and current of Scripture-expreſſions doth hold forth <hi>the continuance of childrens memberſhip in the viſible church</hi> from the beginning to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſeed or children who become members together with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic: </seg>4</label> (<hi>i.e.</hi> by means of their parents covenanting) <hi>are children in minority.</hi> This appears, 1. Becauſe ſuch children are <hi>holy</hi> by their parents covenanting, who would <hi>elſe be unclean,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14 but they would not elſe neceſſarily be unclean, if they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ult; for then they might act for themſelves, and ſo be holy by their perſonal covenanting: Neither on the other hand would they neceſſarily be <hi>holy,</hi> if adult, (as he aſſerts the children there to be) for they might continue Pagans: Therefore the Apoſtle intends onely infants or children in minority. 2. It is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that carries evidence of light and reaſon with it, as to all tranſactions, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, that <hi>if a man be of age he ſhould anſwer for himſelf, John</hi> 9.21. They that are come to years of diſcretion, ſo as to <hi>have knowledge and underſtanding,</hi> fit to act in a matter of that nature, are to covenant by their own perſonal act, <hi>Neh.</hi> 10.28, 29. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44 5, 3. They that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly taken in with their parents, are reputed to be viſible <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of the covenant, and avouchers of God</hi> to be their God, <hi>Deut:</hi> 26.7, 18. with <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11, 12 But if adult children ſhould, without regard to their own perſonal act, be taken in with their parents, then ſome might be reputed <hi>entertainers,</hi> that are manifeſt <hi>rejecters</hi> of the covenant: for ſo an adult ſon or daughter of a godly parent may be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is requiſite to the memberſhip of children,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic: </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>that the next parents, one or both, be in covenant.</hi> For although after-generations have no ſmall benefit by their pious Anceſtors, who derive federal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to their ſucceeding generations, in caſe they keep their ſtanding in the covenant, and be not apoſtates from it; yet the piety of Anceſtors ſufficeth not, unleſs the next parent <hi>continue</hi> in covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 22. 1. Becauſe if the next parent be cut or broken off, the following ſeed are broken off alſo, <hi>Exod:</hi> 20.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 17, 19, 20. as the Gentile believing parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were taken in; ſo the Jews, parents and children, were then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94891:16"/>broken off. 2. One of the parents muſt be a believer, or <hi>elſe the children are unclean,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7 14.3. If children may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted members and baptized, though the next parents be not in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, then the Church ſhould be bound to baptize thoſe, whom ſhe can have <hi>no power over, nor hope concerning,</hi> to ſee them brought up in the true Chriſtian Religion, and under the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: For the next parents being wicked, and not in covenant, may carry away, and bring up their children <hi>to ſerve other Gods.</hi> 4. If we ſtop not at the next parent, but grant that Anceſtors may, notwithſtanding the apoſtacy of the next parents, convey memberſhip unto children, then we ſhould want a ground where to ſtop, and then all the children on earth ſhould have right to memberſhip and Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Infant-ſeed of confederate viſible Believers, are members of the ſame Church with their parents, and when grown up, are perſonally under the Watch, Diſcipline and Government of that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That they are members of the ſame Church with their parents,</hi> appears; 1. Becauſe ſo were <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Family-church, and the children of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Proſelytes</hi> of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> National Church: and there is the ſame reaſon for <hi>children</hi> now to be of the <hi>ſame Congregational Church</hi> with their parents. Chriſt's care for children, and the ſcope of the Covenant, as to obligation unto Order and Government, is as great now, as then. 2. Either they are members of the ſame Church with their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or of ſome other Church, or Non-members: But neither of the latter; therefore the former. That they are not Non-members, was before proved in <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Partic.</hi> 3. and if not members of the <hi>ſame Church</hi> with their parents, then <hi>of no other.</hi> For if there be not reaſon ſufficient to ſtate them members of that Church where their parents have covenanted for them, and where ordinarily they are baptized and do inhabit, then much leſs is there reaſon to make them members of any other: and ſo they will be members of no particular Church at all; and it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94891:17"/>ſhewed, that there is no ordinary and orderly ſtanding eſtate of Church-members, but in ſome particular Church. 3. <hi>The ſame covenant-act is accounted the act of parent and-childe:</hi> but the parents covenanting rendred himſelf a member of this particular Church; Therefore ſo it renders the childe alſo. How can chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren come in with and by their parents, and yet come into a Church, wherein and whereof their parents are not, ſo as that they ſhould be of one Church, and the parents of another? 4. Children are in <hi>an orderly and regular ſtate:</hi> for they are in that ſtate, wherein the order of Gods Covenant, and his inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein, hath placed them; they being members by vertue of the Covenant of God. To ſay their ſtanding is diſorderly, would be to impute diſorder to the order of Gods Covenant, or irregularity to the Rule. Now all will grant it to be moſt order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and regular, that every Chriſtian be a member in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, and in that particular Church, where his regular habitation is; which to children uſually is, where their parents are. If the Rule call them to remove, then their memberſhip ought orderly to be tranſlated to the Church, whither they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move. Again, order requires that <hi>the childe,</hi> and the <hi>power of government over the childe,</hi> ſhould go together. It would <hi>bring ſhame</hi> and confuſion for the childe to be from under government, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15. and Parental and Eccleſiaſtical government con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring, do mutually help and ſtrengthen each other. Hence the parent and the childe muſt be members of the ſame Church; unleſs the childe be by ſome ſpecial providence ſo removed, as that ſome other perſon hath the power over him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That when theſe children are grown up, they are perſonally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Watch, Diſcipline and Government of that Church,</hi> is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: for, 1. Children were under <hi>Patriarchal</hi> and <hi>Moſaical</hi> diſcipline of old, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.9, 10, 12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. and therefore under <hi>Congregational</hi> diſcipline now. 2. They are <hi>within</hi> the Church, or members thereof, (as hath been, and after will be further proved) and therefore ſubject to Church-judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. 3. They are <hi>diſciples,</hi> and therefore under <hi>diſcipline</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſchool, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. 4. They are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94891:17"/>
               <hi>in Church-covenant,</hi> therefore ſubject to <hi>Church-power, Gen:</hi> 17.7. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.19. 5. They are <hi>ſubjects of the kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> and therefore under the laws and government of his Kingdome, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.25, 26. 6. <hi>Baptiſm</hi> leaves the baptized (of which number theſe children are) in a ſtate of ſubjection to the <hi>authoritative teaching</hi> of Chriſt's Miniſters, and to the <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all his commandments, Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. and therefore in a ſtate of ſubjection unto Diſcipline. 7. Elders are charged <hi>to take heed unto, and to feed</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> both to teach and rule, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.3, 4.) <hi>all the flock</hi> or Church, <hi>over which the holy Ghoſt hath made them overſeers, Acts</hi> 20.28. That children are a part of the flock, was before proved: and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> accounts them, writing to the ſame flock or Church of <hi>Epheſus, Eph</hi> 6.1. 8. Otherwiſe Irreligion and Apoſtacy would inevitably break in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Churches, and no Church-way left by Chriſt to prevent or heal the ſame: which would alſo bring many Church-members under that dreadful judgement of being <hi>let alone</hi> in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Adult perſons are not therefore to be admitted to full Communion, meerly becauſe they are and continue members, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch further qualifications, as the Word of God requireth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth hereof is plain, 1. From 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28, 29. where it is required, that ſuch as come to the Lords Supper, be able <hi>to examine themſelves, and to diſcern the Lords body;</hi> elſe they will <hi>eat and drink unworthily, and eat and drink damnation,</hi> or judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>to themſelves,</hi> when they partake of this Ordinance. But meer memberſhip is ſeparable from ſuch ability to examine one's ſelf, and diſcern the Lords body: as in the children of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that grow up to years is too often ſeen. 2. In the Old Tes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament, though men did continue members of the Church, yet for ceremonial uncleanneſs they were to be kept from full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the holy things, <hi>Levit.</hi> 7, 20, 21. <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.13, 20. yea and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Porters</hi> in the Old Teſtament had
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94891:18"/>ſpecial charge committed to them, that men <hi>ſhould not partake in all the holy things,</hi> unleſs duely qualified for the ſame, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their memberſhip, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 22.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 44.7, 8, 9, 23. and therefore much more in theſe times, where moral funeſs and ſpiritual qualifications are wanting, <hi>memberſhip alone</hi> is not ſufficient for <hi>full communion.</hi> More was required to adult perſons <hi>eating the Paſſeover,</hi> then meer memberſhip: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo there is now to the Lords Supper. For they were <hi>to eat to the Lord, Exodus</hi> 12.14. which is expounded in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. where, <hi>keeping the Paſſeover to the Lord, verſe</hi> 5. imports and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires exerciſing Repentance, <hi>verſe</hi> 6, 7. their actual giving up themſelves to the Lord, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>heart-preparation</hi> for it, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. and <hi>holy rejoycing before the Lord, verſe</hi> 21, 25. See the like in <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.21, 22. 3. Though all members of the Church are ſubjects of Baptiſm, they and their children, yet all members may not partake of the Lords Supper, as is further manifeſt from the different nature of Baptiſm and the Lords Supper. Baptiſm firſtly and properly ſeals <hi>covenant-holineſs,</hi> as circumciſion did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Church-memberſhip,</hi> Rom: 15.8. <hi>planting into Christ, Rom.</hi> 6. and ſo members, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> are the ſubjects of Baptiſm, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. But the Lords Supper is the Sacrament <hi>of growth in Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>ſpecial communion</hi> with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. which ſuppoſeth <hi>a ſpecial renewing and exerciſe</hi> of Faith and Repentance in thoſe that partake of that Ordinance. Now if perſons, even when adult, may be and continue members, and yet be debarred from the Lords Supper, until meet qualifications for the ſame do appear in them; then may they alſo (until like qualifications) be debarred from that power of <hi>Voting</hi> in the Church, which pertains to Males in full communion. It ſeems not rational, that thoſe who are not themſelves fit for all Ordinances, ſhould have ſuch an influence referring to all Ordinances, as Voting in Election of Officers, Admiſſion and Cenſures of Members, doth import. For how can they who are not able <hi>to examine and judge themſelves,</hi> be thought able and fit to <hi>diſcern and judge</hi> in the weighty affairs of the houſe of God? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28, 31. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 12.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94891:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Church-members who were admitted in minority, underſtanding the Doctrine of Faith, and publickly profeſſing their aſſent thereto; not ſcandalous in life, and ſolemnly owning the Covenant before the Church, wherein they give up themſelves and their children to the Lord, and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Christ in the Church, their children are to be Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is evident from the Arguments following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe children are partakers of that which is the main ground of baptizing any children whatſoever,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>and neither the parents nor the children do put in any barre to hinder it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That they partake of that which is the main ground of bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing any,</hi> is clear; Becauſe intereſt in the Covenant is the main ground of title to Baptiſm, and this theſe children have. 1. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the covenant is the main ground of title to Baptiſm;</hi> for ſo in the Old Teſtament this was the ground of title to Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Gen</hi> 17.7, 9, 10, 11. to which Baptiſm now anſwers, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. and in <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39 they are on this ground exhorted to <hi>be baptized,</hi> becauſe <hi>the promiſe</hi> or covenant <hi>was to them and to their children.</hi> That a member, or one in covenant, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> is the ſubject of Baptiſm, was further cleared before in <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>That theſe children have intereſt in the covenant,</hi> appears; Becauſe <hi>if the parent be in covenant, the childe is alſo:</hi> for the covenant is to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and <hi>their ſeed in their generations,</hi> Gen: 17.7, 9. <hi>The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is to you and to your children, Acts</hi> 2.39. If the parent <hi>ſtand,</hi> in the Church, ſo doth the childe, among the Gentiles now, as well as among the jews of old, <hi>Rom:</hi> 11.16, 20, 21, 22. It is unheard of in Scripture, that the progreſs of the covenant ſtops at the infant childe. But <hi>the parents in queſtion are in covenant,</hi> as appears. 1. Becauſe they were once in covenant, and never ſince diſcovenanted. If they had not once been in covenant, they had not warrantably been baptized; and they are ſo ſtill, except in ſome way of God they have been diſcovenanted, caſt out, or cut off from their covenant-relation, which theſe have not been: neither are perſons once in covenant, <hi>broken off</hi> from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94891:19"/>it according to Scripture, ſave for notórious ſin, and incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs therein, <hi>Rom</hi> 11.20. which is not the caſe of theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents. 2 Becauſe the tenor of the covenant is <hi>to the faithfull and their ſeed after them in their generations, Gen:</hi> 17.7 even <hi>to a thouſand generations, i. e.</hi> conditionally, provided that the parents ſucceſſively do continue to be <hi>keepers</hi> of the covenant, <hi>Exod:</hi> 20.6 <hi>Deut:</hi> 7:9, 11 <hi>Pſalm</hi> 105:8. which the parents in queſtion are, becauſe they are not (in Scripture account in this caſe) <hi>forſakers or rejecters</hi> of the God and Covenant of their fathers: ſee <hi>Deut:</hi> 29.25, 26. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17: 15-20. 2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 7: 22 <hi>Deut:</hi> 7: 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That theſe parents in queſtion <hi>do not put in any barre to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> their children from Baptiſm, is plain from the words of the Propoſition, wherein they are deſcribed to be ſuch as <hi>underſtand the doctrine of Faith, and publikely profeſs their aſſent thereto:</hi> therefore they put not in any barre of groſs Ignorance, Atheiſm, Hereſie or Infidelity: Alſo they are <hi>not ſcandalous in life, but ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly own the covenant before the Church;</hi> therefore they put not in any barre of Profaneneſs, or Wickedneſs, or Apoſtacy from the covenant, whereinto they entred in minority. That the infant-children in queſtion do themſelves put in any barre, none will imagine.</p>
            <p>The children of the parents in queſtion are <hi>either children of the covenant,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>or ſtrangers from the covenant,</hi> Eph: 2: 12. <hi>either holy or unclean,</hi> 1 Cor: 7: 14. either <hi>within</hi> the Church or <hi>without,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5: 12, either ſuch as <hi>have God for their God,</hi> or <hi>without God in the world,</hi> Eph: 2: 12. But he that conſiders the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will not affirm <hi>the latter</hi> concerning theſe children: and <hi>the forme,</hi> being granted, infers their right to Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>To deny the Propoſition, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>3</label> would be, 1. To ſtraiten the grace of Chriſt in the Goſpel-diſpenſation, and to make the Church in New Teſtament-times in a worſe caſe, relating to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſucceſſively, then were the Jews of old. 2. To render the children of the Jews when they ſhall be called, in a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then under the legal adminiſtration; contrary to <hi>Jer:</hi> 30: 20. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37: 25, 26. 3. To deny the application of the initiatory Seal to ſuch as regularly ſtand in the Church and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94891:19"/>to whom the <hi>Moſaical</hi> diſpenſation, nay the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution in the covenant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> appointed it to be applied, <hi>Gen:</hi> 17: 9, 10. <hi>John</hi> 7.22, 23. 4. <hi>To break Gods covenant</hi> by denying the initiatory Seal to thoſe that are in covenant, <hi>Gen:</hi> 17: 9, 10, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Confederate viſible Believers, though but in the loweſt degree ſuch,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>are to have their children baptized;</hi> witneſs the practice of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>the Apoſiles,</hi> who baptized perſons upon the <hi>firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> of their Chriſtianity. But the parents in queſtion <hi>are confederate viſible Believers,</hi> at leaſt <hi>in ſome degree:</hi> For, 1. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may obſerve in them ſundry poſitive Arguments for it; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the terms of the Propoſition, and nothing evident againſt it. 2. <hi>Children of the godly</hi> qualified but as the perſons in the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, are ſaid to be <hi>faithfull, Tit:</hi> 1.6. 3. Children of the Covenant as the Parents in queſtion are) have frequently the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of grace wrought in them in younger years, as Scripture and experience ſhews: Inſtance, <hi>Joſeph, Samuel David, Solomon, Abijah Joſiah, Daniel, John Baptiſt</hi> and <hi>Timothy.</hi> Hence <hi>this ſort</hi> of perſons ſhewing nothing to the contrary, are in charity, or to Eccleſiaſtical reputation, viſible Believers. 4. They that are regularly in the Church (as the Parents in queſtion be) are <hi>viſible Saints</hi> in the account of Scripture (which is the account of truth:) for the Church is, in Scripture-account, a company of <hi>Saints,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 14: 33. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.2. 5. Being in covenant and bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, they have Faith and Repentance <hi>indefinitely given</hi> to them in the Promiſe, and ſealed up in Baptiſm, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30: 6. which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues valid, and ſo a valid teſtimony for them, while they do not reject it. Yet it doth not neceſſarily follow, that theſe perſons are immediately fit for the Lords Supper; becauſe though they are <hi>in a latitude of expreſſion</hi> to be accounted viſible Believers, or <hi>in numero fidelium,</hi> as even infants in covenant are, yet they may want that ability to examine themſelves, and that ſpecial exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Faith, which is requiſite to that Ordinance; as was ſaid upon <hi>Propoſ</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The denial of Baptiſm to the children in queſtion,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>hath a dangerous tendency to Irreligion and Apoſtacy;</hi> becauſe it denies them, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94891:20"/>ſo the children of the Church ſucceſſively, <hi>to have any part in the Lord;</hi> which is the way to make them <hi>ceaſe from fearing the Lord, Joſh</hi> 22.24, 25, 27. For if they <hi>have a part in the Lord, i. e.</hi> a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Iſrael, and ſo in the Lord the God of Iſrael, then they are in the Church, or members of it, and ſo to be baptized, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1. The owning of the children of thoſe that ſucceſſively continue in covenant to be <hi>a part of the Church,</hi> is ſo far from being deſtructive to the purity and proſperity of the Church, and of Religion therein, (as ſome conceive) that this imputation belongs to the contrary Tenet. To ſeek to be more pure then the Rule, will ever end in impurity in the iſſue. God hath ſo framed his covenant, and conſequently the conſtitution of his Church thereby, as to deſign a continuation and propagation of his Kingdome therein, from one generation to another. Hence the covenant runs <hi>to us and to our ſeed after us in their generations.</hi> To keep in the line, and under the influence and efficacy of this covenant of God, is the true way to the Churches glory: To cut it off and diſavow it, cuts off the proſperity of <hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; hinders it from being (as in the moſt glorious times it ſhall be) <hi>an eternal excellency, and the joy of many generations.</hi> This progreſs of the covenant <hi>eſtabliſheth</hi> the Church, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29 13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.20. The contrary therefore doth diſeſtabliſh it. This obligeth and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageth to the conveyance of Religion down to after-generations; the care whereof is ſtrictly commanded, and highly approved by the Lord, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 78.4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. This continues a nurſery ſtill in Chriſt's Orchard or <hi>Vineyard, Iſa.</hi> 5.1, 7. the contrary neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects that, and ſo lets the whole run to ruine. Surely God was an holy God, and loved the purity and glory of the Church in the Old Teſtament: but then he went in this way of a ſucceſſive progreſs of the covenant to that end, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.11. If ſome did then, or do now decline to <hi>unbelief</hi> and apoſtacy, that doth not make <hi>the faith of God</hi> in his covenant <hi>of none effect,</hi> or <hi>the advantage</hi> of intereſt therein inconſiderable: yea the more holy, reforming and glorious that the times are or ſhall be, the more eminently is a ſucceſſive continuation and propagation of the Church therein deſigned, promiſed and intended, <hi>Iſa</hi> 60.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 59.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.25 -28. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.16-28. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94891:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The parents in queſtion are perſonal, immediate,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum: </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>and yet-continuing members of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That they are <hi>perſonal members,</hi> or members in their own perſons, appears, 1. Becauſe they are perſonally <hi>holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Co.</hi> 7 14. not parents onely, but [your children] are holy. 2. They are perſonally baptized, or have had Baptiſm, the ſeal of memberſhip, applied to their own perſons: which being regularly done, is a divine teſtimony that they are in their own perſons members of the Church. 3 They are perſonally under diſcipline, and liable to Church-cenſures in their own perſons; <hi>vide Propoſ.</hi> 3. 4. They are perſonally (by means of the covenant) in a viſible ſtate of ſalvation. To ſay they are not members in their own perſons, but in their parents, would be as if one ſhould ſay, They are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their parents, and not in their own perſons. 5. When they <hi>commit iniquity,</hi> they perſonally <hi>break the covenant;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are perſonally in it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.2, 10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the like Reaſons it appears that children are <hi>immediate members,</hi> as to the eſſence of memberſhip, (<hi>i. e.</hi> that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own perſons are the immediate ſubjects of this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct of Church-memberſhip) though they come to it by means of their parents covenanting. For as touching that diſtinction of <hi>mediate and immediate,</hi> as applied to memberſhip (which ſome urge) we are to diſtinguiſh 1. between the efficient and the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of memberſhip: 2. between the inſtrumental efficient or means thereof, which is the parents profeſſion and covenanting; and the principal efficient, which is divine Inſtitution. They may be ſaid to be <hi>mediate</hi> (or rather <hi>mediately</hi>) members, as they become members <hi>by means</hi> of their parents covenanting, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental cauſe thereof: but that doth nothing vary or diminiſh <hi>the eſſence</hi> of their memberſhip. For divine Inſtitution giveth or granteth a real and perſonal memberſhip unto them, as well as unto their parents, and maketh the parent a publick perſon, and ſo his act theirs to that end. Hence the eſſence of memberſhip, <hi>i. e. Covenant-intereſt, or a place and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion within the viſible Church,</hi> is really, properly, perſonally and immediately the portion of the childe by divine gift and grant. <hi>Josh.</hi> 22 25, 27. their <hi>children have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94891:21"/>a part in the Lord,</hi> as well as themſelves. <hi>A part in the Lord</hi> there, and <hi>Church-memberſhip</hi> (or <hi>memberſhip in Iſrael</hi>) are terms equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent. Now <hi>the children</hi> there, and <hi>a part in the Lord,</hi> are <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> and <hi>Adjunct,</hi> which nothing comes between, ſo as to ſever the Adjunct from the Subject; therefore they are <hi>immediate ſubjects</hi> of that Adjunct, or <hi>immediate members.</hi> Again, their viſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffing into Chriſt the head, and ſo into the Church his body, is ſealed in their Baptiſm: but in ingraffing nothing comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the graft and the ſtock: Their union is immediate; hence they are immediately inſerted into the viſible Church, or imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate members thereof. The <hi>little children</hi> in <hi>Deut</hi> 29.11. were perſonally and immediately a part of <hi>the people of God,</hi> or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church of Iſrael, as well as the parents. To be in covenant, or to be <hi>a covenantee,</hi> is the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of a Church-member. If one come to be in covenant one way, and another in another, but both are in covenant or covenantees, (<hi>i. e.</hi> parties with whom the covenant is made, and whom God takes into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant) as the children here are, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.8. then both are in their own perſons the <hi>immediate</hi> ſubjects of the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of memberſhip, and ſo immediate members. To <hi>act</hi> in covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is but the inſtrumental means of memberſhip and yet chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not without this neither. For the act of the parent (their publick perſon) is accounted theirs, and they are ſaid to <hi>enter into covenant, Deut.</hi> 29.11, 12. So that what is it that Children want unto an actual, compleat, proper, abſolute and immediate memberſhip? (ſo far as theſe terms may with any propriety or pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy be applied to the matter in hand.) Is it <hi>Covenant-intereſt,</hi> which is the <hi>formalis ratio</hi> of memberſhip? No, they are in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Is it <hi>divine grant and inſtitution,</hi> which is the <hi>principal efficient?</hi> No: he hath clearly declared himſelf, that he grants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to the children of his people a portion in his Church, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points them to be members thereof. Is it <hi>an act of covenanting,</hi> which is the <hi>inſtrumental means?</hi> No: they have this alſo reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively by divine appointment, making the parent a <hi>publik perſon,</hi> and accounting them to covenant in his covenanting A diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner and means of conveying the covenant to us, or of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94891:21"/>making us members, doth not make a different ſort of memberſhip <hi>We</hi> now are as truly, perſonally and immediately members of the body of faln mankinde, and by nature heirs of the condemnation pertaining thereto, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, though he came to be ſo by is <hi>own perſonal act,</hi> and we by <hi>the act of our publick perſon.</hi> If a Prince give ſuch Lands to a man and his heirs ſucceſſively, while they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue loyal; the following heir is a true and immediate owner of that Land, and may be perſonally diſ inherited, if diſloyal, as well as his father before him. A member is one that is according to Rule (or according to divine Inſtitution) <hi>within</hi> the viſible Church. Thus the child is properly, &amp; perſonally or immediately. <hi>Paul</hi> eaſts all men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two ſorts, thoſe <hi>within,</hi> and thoſe <hi>without,</hi> i.e. <hi>members,</hi> and <hi>non-members,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. It ſeems he knew of no ſuch diſtinction of <hi>mediate and immediate;</hi> as puts a <hi>medium</hi> between theſe two. <hi>Object.</hi> If children be compleat and immediate members as their parents are, then they ſhall immediately have all Church-priviledges, as their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents have without any further act or qualification <hi>Anſ.</hi> It followeth not. All priviledges that belong to members, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> do belong to the children as well as the parents: But all Church-priviledges do not ſo. A member as ſuch, (or all members) may not partake of all priviledges; but they are to make progreſs both in memberly duties and priviledges, as their age, capacity and qualifications do fit them for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That their memberſhip ſtill continues in adult age, and ceaſeth not with their infancy,</hi> appears, 1. Becauſe in Scripture perſons are <hi>broken off,</hi> onely for notorious ſin or incorrigible impenitency and unbelief, not for growing up to adult age, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. 2. <hi>The Jew children cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed</hi> did not ceaſe to be members by growing up, but continued in the Church, and were by virtue of their memberſhip received in infancy, bound unto various duties, and in ſpecial unto thoſe ſolemn perſonal profeſſions that pertained to adult members, not as then entring into <hi>a new memberſhip,</hi> but as making a progreſs in <hi>memberly duties, Deut.</hi> 26.2-10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.16, 17 with <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. 3. Thoſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>born-ſervants</hi> and <hi>ſubjects,</hi> which the Scripture makes uſe of to ſet forth the ſtate of children in the Church by, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25 41 42. <hi>Ezek</hi> 37.25 do not, (as all men know) ceaſe with infancy but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in adult age. Whence alſo it follows, that one ſpecial end of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94891:22"/>memberſhip received in infancy, is to leave perſons under engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſervice and ſubjection to Chriſt in his Church, when grown up, when they are fitteſt for it, and have moſt need of it. 4. There is no ordinary way of ceſſation of memberſhip but by <hi>Death, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, Excommunication,</hi> or <hi>Diſſolution of the Society:</hi> none of which is the caſe of the perſons in queſtion. 5. Either they are when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ult, members or non-members: if non-members, then a perſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteed a member and ſealed by Baptiſm, not caſt out, nor deſerving ſo to be, may (the Church whereof he was ſtill remaining) become a non-member and out of the Church, and of the unclean world; which the Scripture acknowledgeth not; Now if the parent ſtand member of the Church, the childe is a member alſo; For now <hi>the root is holy,</hi> therefore <hi>ſo are the branches, Rom.</hi> 11.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. The parent is in covenant, therefore ſo is the childe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. and if the childe be a member of the viſible Church, then he is a ſubject of Baptiſm, according to <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition 6<hi rend="sup">t.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such Church-members, who either by death, or ſome other extraordinary Providence, have been inevitably hindred from publick acting as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, yet have given the Church cauſe in judgment of charity, to look at them as ſo qualified, and ſuch as had they been called thereunto, would have ſo acted, their children are to be Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is manifeſt. 1. Becauſe the main foundation of the right of the childe to priviledge remains, viz: Gods inſtitution, and the force of his covenant carrying it to the generations of ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue keepers of the covenant, <hi>i. e.</hi> not viſibly breakers of it. By virtue of which <hi>inſtitution and covenant,</hi> the children in queſtion are members, and their membership being diſtinct from the parents membership, ceaſeth not, but continues notwithſtanding the parents deceaſe or neceſſary abſence: and if members, then ſubjects of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm. 2. Becauſe the parents not doing what is required in the <hi>fifth Propoſition,</hi> is through want of oppotunity; which is not to be imputed as their guilt ſo as to be a barre to the childes priviledge. 3. God reckoneth that is done in his ſervice to which there was manifeſt deſire and endeavour, albeit the acting of it were hindred; as in <hi>David</hi> to build the Temple, 1 <hi>Kings</hi>8. 18, 19 in <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 17. according to that in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Where
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94891:22"/>there is a willing minde, it is accepted according to what a man hath, and not according to what he hath not:</hi> which is true of this Church-duty, as well as of that of Alms. It is an uſual phraſe with the Ancients to ſtyle ſuch and ſuch Martyrs <hi>in voto,</hi> and baptized <hi>in voto,</hi> becauſe there was no want of deſire that way, though their deſire was not actually accompliſhed 4. The terms of the Propoſition import that in charity, that is here done <hi>interpretatively,</hi> which is mentioned to be done in the fifth propoſition <hi>expreſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Propoſition</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The members of Orthodox Churches, being ſound in the Faith, and not ſcandalous in life, and preſenting due teſtimony thereof; theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally comming from one Church to another, may have their children Baptized in the church whither they come, by virtue of Communion of Churches: but if they remove their habitation, they ought orderly to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Chriſt in the Church where they ſettle their abode, and ſo their children to be Baptized. It being the churches duty to receive ſuch unto commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo farre as they are regularly fit for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Such members of other Churches as are here deſcribed, occaſionally coming from one Church to another, their children are to be baptized in the Church whither they come, by virtue of Communion of Churches:</hi> 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that is regularly a member of a true particular Church, is a ſubject of Baptiſm, according to <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> But the children of the parents here deſcribed are ſuch, according to <hi>Propoſition</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> therefore they are meet and lawful ſubjects of Baptiſm, or have right to be baptized. And <hi>Communion of Churches</hi> infers ſuch acts as this is, <hi>viz:</hi> to baptize a fit ſubject of Baptiſm, though a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of another Church, when the ſame is orderly deſired. (See <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form of Diſcipline, chap.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4.) For look as every Church hath a double conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Of its own conſtitution and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion within it ſelf; 2. Of that communion which it holds and ought to maintain with other Churches: So the Officer <hi>(the Paſtor or Teacher)</hi> thereof, is there ſet, 1. To adminiſter to this Church <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly;</hi> 2. To do acts of Communion <hi>occaſionally,</hi> (<hi>viz:</hi> ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to his Office, as <hi>Baptizing</hi> doth) reſpecting the members of other Churches, with whom this Church holds or ought to hold communion. 2. To refuſe communion with a true Church <hi>in law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94891:23"/>and pious actions,</hi> is unlawful, and juſtly accounted Schiſmatical. For if the Church be true, Chriſt holdeth ſome communion with it; therefore ſo muſt we: but if we will not have communion with it in thoſe acts that are good and pious, then in none at all. <hi>Total ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> from a true Church, is unlawful: But to deny communion in good actions, is to make a total ſeparation. Now to baptize a fit ſubject, as is the childe in queſtion, is <hi>a lawfull and pious action,</hi> and therefore <hi>by virtue of Communion of Churches,</hi> in the caſe mentioned to be attended. And if <hi>Baptiſm lawfully adminiſtred,</hi> may and ought to be <hi>received</hi> by us for our children in another true Church, where Providence ſo caſts us, as that we cannot have it in our own, (as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it may and ought to be:) then alſo we may and ought in like caſe to <hi>diſpenſe Baptiſm,</hi> when deſired, <hi>to a man and lawfull ſubject,</hi> being a member of another Church. To deny or refuſe either of theſe, would be an unjuſtifiable refuſing of Communion of Churches, and tending to ſinful ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Such as remove their habitation, ought orderly to covenant and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject themſelves to the Government of Chriſt in the Church, where they ſetlle their abode, and ſo their children to be baptized;</hi> 1. Becauſe the regularly baptized <hi>are diſciples,</hi> and under the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſt: But they that are abſolutely removed from the Church whereof they were, ſo as to be uncapable of being under Diſcipline there, ſhall be under it no where, if not in the Church where they inhabit. They that would have <hi>Church-priviledges,</hi> ought to be <hi>under Church-power:</hi> But theſe will be under no Church-power, but <hi>as lambs in a large place,</hi> if not under it there where their ſetled abode is. 2. Every Chriſtian ought to covenant for himſelf and his children, or profeſſedly to give up himſelf and his to the Lord and than <hi>in the way of his Ordinances, Deut.</hi> 26 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.5. and <hi>explicite covenanting</hi> is a duty, eſpecially where we are called to it, and have opportunity for it: nor can they well be ſaid to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>implicitely,</hi> that do <hi>explicitely</hi> refuſe a profeſſed covenanting, when called thereunto And eſpecially this covenanting is a duty, when we would partake of ſuch a Church-priviledge, as Baptiſm for our children is. But the parents in queſtion will now be <hi>profeſſed co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters</hi> no where, if not in the Church where their fixed habitation is. Therefore they <hi>ought orderly to covenant there, and ſo their children
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94891:23"/>to be baptized.</hi> 3. To <hi>refuſe</hi> covenanting and ſubjection to Chriſt's Government in the Church where they live, being ſo removed, as to be utterly uncapable of it elſwhere, would be <hi>a walking diſorderly,</hi> and would too much favour of <hi>profaneneſs and ſeparation;</hi> and hence to adminiſter Baptiſm to the children of ſuch as <hi>ſtand in that way,</hi> would be to adminiſter Chriſt's Ordinances to ſuch as are in <hi>a way of ſin and diſorder;</hi> which ought not to be, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. and would be contrary to that Rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. II. <hi>VVHether according to the Word of God there ought to be a Conſociation of Churches, and what ſhould be the manner of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Anſwer may be briefly given in the Propoſitions following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Every Church or particular Congregation of viſible Saints in Goſpel-order, being furniſhed with a Presbytery, at leaſt with a Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Elder, and walking together in truth and peace, hath received from the Lord Jeſus full power and authority Eccleſiaſtical within it ſelf, regularly to adminiſter all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and is not under any other Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction whatſoever.</hi> For to ſuch a Church Chriſt hath <hi>given the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven, that what they binde or looſe on earth, ſhall be bound or looſed in heaven,</hi> Matt. 16.19. &amp; 18.17, 18. Elders are <hi>ordained in every Church.</hi> Acts 14.23. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. and are therein authorized officially to adminiſter in the Word, Prayer, Sacraments and Cenſures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.4, 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.5. The reproving of the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> and of the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, imports they had power, each of them within themſelves, to reform the abuſes that were amongſt them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2 14, 20. Hence it follows, that Conſociation of Churches is not to hinder the exerciſe of this power, but by counſel from the Word of God to direct and ſtrengthen the ſame upon all juſt occaſions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Churches of Chriſt do ſtand in a ſiſterly relation each to other,</hi> Cant. 8.8 <hi>being united in the ſame Faith and Order,</hi> Eph. 4.5. Col. 2.5. <hi>to walk by the ſame Rule,</hi> Phil. 3.16: <hi>in the exerciſe of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94891:24"/>ſame Ordinances for the ſame ends,</hi> Eph. 4 11, 12, 13. 1 Cor. 16.1. <hi>under one and the ſame political Head, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 1.22, 23. &amp; 4.5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. Which Union infers a Communion ſutable thereunto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Communion of Churches is the faithfull improvement of the gifts of Chriſt beſtowed upon them for his ſervice and glory, and their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall good and edification, according to capacity and opportunity.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.10, 11. 1 Cor. 12.4, 7. &amp; 10.24. 1 Cor. 3.21, 22. Cantic 8.9. Rom 1.15. Gal. 6.10.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Acts of Communion of Churches are ſuch as theſe:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Hearty Care and Prayer one for another,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.28. Cant. 8.8 Rom. 1.9. Coloſſ. 1.9. Eph. 6.18.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To afford Relief by communication of their Gifts in Temporal or Spiritual neceſſities,</hi> Rom. 15.26, 27. Acts 11.22, 29. 2 Cor. 8.1, 4, 14.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To maintain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace, by giving account one to another of their publick actions, when it is orderly deſired,</hi> Acts 11.2, 3, 4-18. Joſh. 22.13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21, 30. 1 Cor. 10 32. <hi>and to ſtrengthen one another in their regular Adminiſtrations; as in ſpecial by a concurrent teſtimony againſt perſons juſtly cenſured,</hi> Acts 15.41. &amp; 16.4, 5. 2 Tim. 4.15. 2 Theſſ. 3.14.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>To ſeek and accept Help from, and give Help unto each other:</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>In caſe of Diviſions and Contentions, whereby the peace of any Church is diſturbed,</hi> Acts 15.2.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>In matters of more then ordinary importance,</hi> [Prov. 24.6. &amp; 15.22] <hi>as Ordination. Tranſlation, and Depoſition of Elders, and ſuch like,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22.</item>
                        <item>3 <hi>In doubtful and difficult Queſtions and Controverſies, Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or Practical, that may ariſe,</hi> Acts 15 2, 6.</item>
                        <item>4. <hi>For the rectifying of mal-Adminiſtrations, and healing of Errours and Scandals, that are unhealed among themſelves,</hi> 3 <hi>John ver:</hi> 9, 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6-11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Rev:</hi> 2: 14, 15 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20, 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13 2. Churches now have need of help in like caſes, as well as Churches then. Chriſt's care is ſtill for whole Churches, as well as for particular perſons; and Apoſtles being now ceaſed, there remains the duty of brotherly love, and mutual care and helpfulneſs incumbent upon Churches, eſpecially Elders for that end.</item>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94891:24"/>
                        <item>5. <hi>In love and faithfulneſs to take notice of the Troubles and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, Errours and Scandals of another Church, and to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter help (when the caſe manifeſtly calls for it) though they ſhould ſo neglect their own good and duty, as not to ſeek it,</hi> Exod. 23.4, 5. Prov. 24.11, 12.</item>
                        <item>6. <hi>To Admoniſh one another when there is need and cauſe for it: and ofter due means with patience uſed, to withdraw from a Church or peccant party therein, obſtinately perſiſting in Errour or Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal;</hi> as in the <hi>Platform of Diſcipline</hi> (<hi>chap.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. <hi>partic.</hi> 3.) is more at large declared: <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11-14. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Conſociation of Churches, is their mutual and ſolemn Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to exerciſe communion in ſuch acts, as aforeſaid, amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with ſpecial reference to thoſe Churches, which by providence are planted in a convenient vicinity, though with liberty reſerved without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to make uſe of others, as the nature of the caſe, or the advantage of opportunity may lead thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The Churches of Chriſt in this Countrey having ſo good opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for it, it is meet to be commended to them, as their duty thus to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate.</hi> For 1. Communion of Churches being commanded, and Conſociation being but an Agreement to practiſe it, this muſt needs be a duty alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.28, 29. 2. <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle ſought with much labour the <hi>conference,</hi> concurrence and <hi>right hand of fellowſhip</hi> of other <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> and ordinary Elders and Churches have not leſs need each of other, to prevent <hi>their running in vain, Gal.</hi> 2.2, 6, 9. 3. Thoſe general Scripture-rules touching the need and uſe of counſel and help in weighty caſes, concern all Societies and Polities, Eccleſiaſtical as well as Civil, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.9, 10, 12. 4. The pattern in <hi>Acts</hi> 15 holds forth a warrant for Councils, which may be greater or leſſer, as the matter ſhall require. 5. Concurrence and Communion of Churches in Goſpel times, is not obſcurely held forth in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.23, 24, 25. <hi>Zeph</hi> 3.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.32, 36. 6. There hath conſtantly been in theſe Churches a profeſſion of Communion, in giving the right hand of fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at the gathering of Churches, and Ordination of Elders: Which importeth a Conſociation, and obligeth to the practice
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94891:25"/>thereof. Without which we ſhould alſo want an expedient and ſufficient Cure for emergent Church-difficulties and Differences: with the want whereof our Way is charged, but unjuſtly, if this part of the Doctrine thereof were duely practiſed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The manner of the Churches agreement herein, or entring into this Conſociation, may be by each Church's open conſenting unto the things here declared in Anſwer to this</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> 
               <hi>Queſtion, as alſo to what is ſaid thereabout in</hi> chap. 15. &amp; 16. <hi>of the</hi> Platform of Diſcipline, <hi>with reference to other Churches in this Colony &amp; Countrey, as in</hi> Propoſ. 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>is before expreſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The manner of exerciſing and practiſing that Communion, which this conſent or agreement ſpecially tendeth unto, may be, by making uſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally of Elders or able Brethren of other Churches; or by the more ſolemn Meetings of both Elders and Meſſengers in leſſer or greater Councils, as the matter ſhall require.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
